<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A model of church-government: or, The grounds of the spirituall frame and government of the house of God. Shewing, what the holy Scriptures have therein delivered; what the best Reformed Churches do practise; what the tender consciences may rest in. For the better satisfaction of such as scruple at the work of reformation, declared and appointed by severall ordinances of Parliament. / By John Dury, one of the Assembly of Divines; who hath travelled heretofore in the work of peace among the churches.</title>
            <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 206 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 45 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A81924</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2873</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E383_26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R21589</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871457</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871457</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160191</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A81924)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160191)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 61:E383[26])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A model of church-government: or, The grounds of the spirituall frame and government of the house of God. Shewing, what the holy Scriptures have therein delivered; what the best Reformed Churches do practise; what the tender consciences may rest in. For the better satisfaction of such as scruple at the work of reformation, declared and appointed by severall ordinances of Parliament. / By John Dury, one of the Assembly of Divines; who hath travelled heretofore in the work of peace among the churches.</title>
                  <author>Dury, John, 1596-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 56 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.R. and E.M. for John Bellamy, and are to be sold at his shop at the three golden Lyons neer the Royall Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aprill 10th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church polity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MODEL OF Church-Government: OR, The GROUNDS of the Spirituall Frame and Government of the Houſe of GOD.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Shewing,</hi> What the <hi>holy Scriptures</hi> have therein delivered; What the beſt <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> do practiſe; What the <hi>Tender Conſciences</hi> may reſt in.</p>
            <p>For the better Satisfaction of ſuch as ſcruple at the Work of REFORMATION, declared and appointed by ſeverall Ordinances of PARLIAMENT.</p>
            <p>BY JOHN DURY, one of the <hi>Aſſembly of Divines;</hi> Who hath travelled heretofore in the work of Peace among the CHURCHES.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>PSAL. 2. 6.</bibl> I have ſet my King upon my holy hill of Zion.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>ISA. 9. 6, 7.</bibl> The government ſhall be upon his ſhoulder, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. R.</hi> and <hi>E. M.</hi> for <hi>John Bellamy,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the three golden Lyons neer the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1647.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. John Gayer, K<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Lord Major of the City of <hi>London. And to the Right Worſhipfull,</hi> The ALDERMEN and SHERIFFS his Brethren.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>heſe Scriptural Aſſertions, at their firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, were not deſigned for the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique; they were only put to Paper at the deſire of thoſe, who in this City gave me a call to the Cure of their ſoules, and were willing to reform their wayes according to the will of God. And becauſe they did confeſſe their ignorance of the whole Frame and Government of the Houſe of GOD; my aime was to let them ſee it, as briefly as I could, in a Model taken from the patern which I have ſeen in the Mount, which the Scriptures have revealed.</p>
            <p>I would not be large, of purpoſe, to the end that I might ſtirre them up the more to Meditation, to the ſearching of the Scriptures, from which I have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to gather all; and to conference with my ſelf,
<pb facs="tcp:160191:3"/> when they ſhould be at a ſtand. I intended nothing, but according to their deſire to give them private ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; yet they would not reſt there, but inſiſted to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage me to publiſh theſe Heads of thoughts (for in effect they are no more:) Nor was it enough to make them publike, but they would have me to owne them, and to preſent you alſo with them. To all which you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that I have condeſcended, although I confeſſe with much reluctancie.</p>
            <p>Not that I am aſhamed to owne any thing that is mine, though ſo imperfect as this is, and in a matter of ſo great conſequence, (for I am very well conſcious to mine own weakneſſe, and not unwilling that others ſhould perceive it, (if it may be for their edification) or that I was doubtfull of any Truth here delivered, (for I conceive that all may be made out to the full, if God ſhould give time, and a call to do it) but that I was loth to offer unto all whom I could not know, that which <hi>I</hi> had deſigned only for a few, whom in caſes of miſtake <hi>I</hi> would be able to rectifie. I was unwilling to ſeem to intermeddle to ſo little purpoſe, as theſe Tracts are like to be, in matters of ſo high concernment, in a ſeaſon ſo full of diſtraction, and in an Age ſo willing to cenſure, ſo apt to miſtake, and ſo ready to miſconſtrue on all hands every thing that hath no character of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiality upon it, though done never ſo harmleſly: And then alſo <hi>I</hi> was afraid to be thought to ſtretch my ſelfe beyond my line, in making this addreſſe unto You. But <hi>I</hi> hope that your favourable acceptance, and the Relation which <hi>I</hi> have to a particular Congregation in the City, will free me from this laſt apprehenſion; and from the former <hi>I</hi> have been taken off, partly by the conſideration of greater inconveniences which might follow upon the
<pb facs="tcp:160191:3"/> not yeelding, then upon the yeelding unto a publication; partly by the importunity of the Call which <hi>I</hi> received to do what here is done. So that <hi>I</hi> hope none other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction will be made of the publication of theſe Notions than ought in charity to be made; which is to believe, That <hi>I</hi> being earneſtly deſired to declare my knowledge of the truth of theſe matters, thought my ſelf bound to beare witnes thereunto, and to ſuffer my teſtimony to come to the light, that it might appeare that theſe works are done in God, that they are free from humane reſpects; and that my aim in putting them forth, is to give occaſion to men conſcionably peaceable, to conſider whether yea or no, an agreement in theſe Truths ought not to oblige Brethren to a neerer conjunction of ſpirits, &amp; profeſſion of unity, then we as yet are come unto? and whether yea or no, the things wherein there is a difference of opinion, deſerve ſo much diſtance in affections, as many are fallen into, or ought to be debated in ſuch a way of heat as moſt men follow, whereby they rather diſturbe then edifie one another. It is a ſad thing to ſee men that are called Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians and Brethren, exerciſing their wits to the diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of one another in Religious matters; and to deale with things concerning Conſcience, lightly, paſſionately, and without all ſerious and conſcionable gravity. Theſe things are to be deplored, but cannot be redreſſed, without the acknowledgement of the Truth; nor can the Truth be received without the ſpirit of Love and Peace, which the Word of the Goſpel doth adminiſter only.</p>
            <p>The Lord of truth and peace reveal the ſame unto us all more and more; and direct You in your ſtation to walk therein as pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns of Righteouſnes before all others. Which, with the wiſhes of proſperity unto the ſettlement of this whole State; ſhall be towards the LORD who alone is able to ſave, the conſtant Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your <hi>HONOURS</hi> moſt humble and affectionate ſervant in Chriſt, JOHN DURY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:4"/>
            <head>A PREFACE To the Chriſtian and unpartiall Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Eeing I am put upon the publiſhing of theſe brief Tracts, I will endeavour by this Preface unto thee to make the beſt uſe thereof that I can, both for mine own comfort, and for the building up of others. As for my ſelf; I ſhall be comforted in this, (whatſoever others may judge of the matter) that I ſee cleerly a Providence in this publication, without any purpoſe of mine: And that I can conceive of the things which I judge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to be imperfections, that they may prove advantages unto Gods main work in his way of uſing them; For the brevity of each Part may, to an intelligent Reader, make the whole ſo much the more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable; and to one that is of no quick underſtanding, although it will be more obſcure, yet it will alſo be leſſe tedious; and may give to him that is ingenious, occaſion to make ſome further inquiry after the Truth, that his rationall Doubts may be ſatisfied; which, as God ſhall enable me with grace, I ſhall be willing to intend.</p>
            <p>As concerning others; ſeeing the ſpirits of moſt men are very ſharp, and full of jealouſies, I ſhall therefore offer my ſelf unto them with the greater ſimplicity; for being in my ſelf without prejudice, I hope to be found towards all without occaſion of offence; and as I ſhall be voyd of partiality, ſo I ſhall make uſe of that liberty which in a buſineſſe of this nature doth beſeem my profeſſion in the Goſpel; which is, to look upon all alike, to be free in the matter, and plain in ſpeeches, to utter the Truth as it is in my heart.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, I think my ſelf bound to declare this; That I am under a Vow to proſecute upon all occaſions, as long as I live, the wayes of Evangelical reconciliation amongſt <hi>PROTESTANTS;</hi> that is to ſay, Profeſſedly to ſeeke, and upon all occaſions offered to advance, amongſt thoſe that have received the Holy Scriptures for their Rule, and keep to the Fundamentals of Faith and Practice, the
<pb facs="tcp:160191:5"/> means of ſpirituall unity, of peace and of love, by the manifeſtation of the truth, and in the duties of holy Communion. Having therefore this opportunity fairly offered; I am obliged, in minding my Vow, to diſcharge a good Conſcience; and for the love which I owe unto the Goſpel of Peace, to the whole Church of God, and to the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and flouriſhing condition thereof in this Nation, to make ſome Overtures, which I hope ſhall give no matter of grievance unto any, but will prove edifying unto all; at leaſt my aim ſhall be none other,<note place="margin">The ſcope of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face.</note> but to ſtir up thy pure minde (Chriſtian Reader) to the thoughts of Brotherly kindneſſe, of meekneſſe, and of peace; to the end that ſome wayes may be taken up, which will help to reconcile the Affections of many divided about Circumſtantials; to preſerve and keep entire the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity which remains about Fundamentals; and to prevent or cure the manifold Miſpriſions, which increaſe our confuſions, and obſtruct the Remedies of our diſeaſes.</p>
            <p>Now to offer at this, I ſhall not cry out againſt particular faults; not becauſe I think them not very hurtfull to the wayes of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or that I think it unlawfull in due time and place, or altogether unuſefull to warne all of publike dangers, when none other Remedies are left: But I ſhall not do it, becauſe it is more ſutable to my ſpirit to ſeek to gain all to the ſenſe of neceſſary Duties, than to reprove ſome for the neglect thereof; becauſe my reſolution is to follow (if it be poſſible) the rule of Charity; firſt to admoniſh a Brother in private, before his faults be charged upon him in publike; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I find it the Theme of many, on all ſides, that do almoſt nothing elſe: And yet this courſe doth prove no lenitive, but rather an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centive to our diſtempers. My way then ſhall be, 1. To repreſent as<note place="margin">The parts of it.</note> briefly as I can, the generall danger which hangeth over all our heads by reaſon of our common faults. 2. To diſcover the cauſes whence our danger doth originally proceed. And 3. to offer at ſome counſel, which may point at a way to prevent the lamentable conſequence which is like to enſue, if no courſe be found and followed for healing of our breaches.</p>
            <p>Firſt concerning the danger wherein we are, thus in brief:</p>
            <p>That we amongſt our ſelves, almoſt in reſpect of every thing, are all broken to peeces in our affections, is very evident.</p>
            <p>That in this rupture of affections there is not only a diſtance of parties, but much heat of oppoſition, no man can deny.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:5"/>
            <p>That by this heat, the alienations and thoughts of heart grow daily greater and greater, every one can perceive.</p>
            <p>That few ſet themſelves in the gap, and labour to make up breach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, all muſt confeſſe.</p>
            <p>And by reaſon of all this, (if the cauſe of our unſettlement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue long) that we ſhall be habituated unto Breaches, even till we be conſumed, none can juſtly doubt, but every one ſhould ſadly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend: becauſe the ſaying of our Lord and Saviour is undeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably true, <hi>That every Kingdom divided againſt it ſelf is brought to deſolation; and every City and Houſe divided againſt it ſelf, ſhall not ſtand,</hi> Mat. 12. 23. If then I may parallel the univerſall ſtate of <hi>Proteſtancie,</hi> as it is oppoſite to <hi>Poperie,</hi> unto a Kingdome; and the Nationall Churches thereof, unto ſo many Cities; and the ſeverall Congregations of each city, unto ſo many Houſes; and in all theſe, if I reflect upon the Breaches which are apparent unto all; Firſt between the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and the <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> which have brought them both from a flouriſhing, to a deſolate condition, in <hi>Germany:</hi> Secondly between each of theſe within themſelves, by their Sub-diviſions and croſſe Parties, which have weakned all their ſtrength, and multiplied ſcandals amongst them: I muſt needs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that Chriſts ſentence is verified upon them; and that the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which of old was denounced and executed againſt <hi>Iſrael,</hi> is now come to paſſe in part upon the <hi>Proteſtant Churches,</hi> and may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed over them all, if the Cauſes thereof be not taken away by true repentance. Let us briefly conſider what the Prophet <hi>Amos,</hi> in his ſixt chapter, ſaith unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that we may apprehend therein our own danger. Firſt he denounceth a heavy woe unto thoſe that were at their eaſe in Zion, and were not grieved at the affliction of <hi>Joſeph;</hi> namely, <hi>That they ſhould be led away captive with the firſt that go captive.</hi> v. 1. till 7. Captivity then is threatned unto all, but chiefly unto theſe. Then he ſheweth the certainty of this judgement, with the means by which, and the chief cauſes for which it ſhould be brought to paſſe. The certainty of the Judgement is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, <hi>v. 8, 9, 10.</hi> namely, that God had ſworne by himſelf, that he did abhorre their excellency and hate their palaces, that he would deliver up the City and all that was in it to the enemies thereof, and that he would kill with death ſuch as remain after the captivity in the city, although there ſhould be but ten men remaining in one houſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:6"/>
            <p>The meanes by which, and the cauſes for which this heavy Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhould be thus executed, are ſet forth in <hi>verſ. 11, 12, 13, 14.</hi> The means are two: He would divide them within themſelves, <hi>v. 11.</hi> and he would bring a forraign Nation againſt them to afflict them, <hi>v. 14.</hi> The cauſes are chiefly two; their incorrigibleneſſe in unrighteouſneſſe, <hi>v. 12.</hi> and their pride in their own ſtrength, <hi>v. 13.</hi> All theſe things are conſiderable in our preſent caſe: For this is evident; although the Church of God is heavily afflicted every where, and the Saints throughout the world have great cauſe to mourn, yet that moſt of us take our eaſe, and reſt contented in the enjoyment of our Victories, and that we grieve for nothing in effect but becauſe we have not all our will accompliſhed againſt the adverſe party with whom we are in conteſt about particular concernments; and as for other things beſides, we are ſecure and careleſſe, we take our pleaſures to the full without reſtraint, and we grieve not at the affliction of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> but in effect we do even as <hi>Joſephs</hi> brethren did, they ſate down to eat bread when they had caſt their Brother into a pit, <hi>Gen. 37. 24, 25.</hi> So we who heretofore have helped to bring our Brethren of the <hi>Palatinate</hi> and of <hi>France,</hi> into the Pit wherein at this day they ſit; now being at our eaſe, we minde not at all their intereſts. If then our ſinne is the ſame with that of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to ſeek our pleaſure and eaſe, and to enjoy it to the full ſo far as we have gotten it; certainly our puniſhment will be the ſame with theirs alſo: for God hath as juſt cauſe to ſweare that he doth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre our excellencie and hate our palaces, as he did theirs; and he hath no leſſe power now to puniſh this Nation with captivity and mortality, then he had heretofore to puniſh that: And to me it is apparent, that he hath ſet the ſame Means awork, and for the ſame Cauſes, againſt us now, which then were threatned againſt them. Againſt them the Prophet threatned, ſaying, <hi>Behold the Lord commandeth; and he will ſmite the great houſe with</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. 11.</note> 
               <hi>breaches, and the little houſe with clefts:</hi> that is, he will divide you, and break your ſtrength to peeces; for, ſaith he, <hi>Shall horſes run upon the rock? will one plow there with oxen? for ye have turned judgement into gall, and the fruit of righteouſneſſe into hemlock.</hi> That is, You muſt be broken to peeces, becauſe<note place="margin">v. 12.</note> you cannot otherwiſe be made ſubject and uſefull unto Gods fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; for you are hardned in your ſinnes like a rock, upon which
<pb facs="tcp:160191:6"/> the ſpirit of God cannot run and have a free paſſage: Nor can<note place="margin">By horſes, Gods ſpirit is typified, <hi>Zach.</hi> 1. 8, 9, 10. compar'd with <hi>c. 6. v.</hi> 2, 3, 4, &amp;c. By oxen, the Miniſters of the Word are typified, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 9, 10, 11. v. 13.</note> you be manured as a profitable husbandry unto him, by his ordinary Miniſtry, which is appointed to plow up your fallow-ground, becauſe you are not capable of being plowed by reaſon of your ſtony heart, which is ſo hardned in the wayes of iniquity, that you have turned Judgement into gall, and the fruit of Righteouſneſſe into hemlock. Moreover, you <hi>rejoyce in a thing of nought,</hi> and you boaſt your ſelves of your ſtrength, ſaying, that <hi>you have taken horns</hi> (power to defend and aſſault) by your own ſtrength: therefore, <hi>behold ſaith the Lord God of hoſts, I will raiſe up againſt you, O houſe of Iſrael, a Nation, and they ſhall afflict you, from the entring in of Hamath, unto the river of the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe.</hi> This is that which was denounced and executed againſt <hi>Iſrael;</hi> this we ſee hath been the caſe of the Proteſtant Churches in <hi>Germanie;</hi> and may we not now ſay unto <hi>England,</hi> or to <hi>Great Britain</hi> in like manner, to this ſame effect—</p>
            <p>Behold the Lord hath commanded in the way of his Juſtice, an evill ſpirit of Diviſion to appeare amongſt you; for he hath ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten your great houſes with breaches, and your little houſes with clefts; there are diviſions and ſubdiviſions amongſt you at home, by which he doth fit you for the ruine which is determined againſt you from abroad, and all by reaſon of your other ſinnes wherein you are hardened; for you pervert Juſtice, and cannot be reformed: becauſe you truſt to the power and ſtrength which you have gotten to your ſelves, therefore God will bring from abroad enemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt you, who ſhall afflict you, as heretofore hath been done to others; Except you feare the Lord, and his goodneſſe by which he doth yet ſpare you, and be ſo wiſe as to prevent this Judgement with ſpeedy Repentance.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of God, this is the danger under which we lie. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Men, all the foundations of the earth, all grounds of ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, all Rules of government, are ſhaken and out of frame. For if we look upon our ſelves in reſpect of that which is within: How little care and compaſſion there is of the Poor, of the oppreſſed and afflicted; how impoſſible it is to expedite the wayes of relief for them; how neer they are to break forth into tumults and diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents: How little faithfulneſſe and truſt there is to be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt men that are called Brethren; how ſome we are of the
<pb facs="tcp:160191:7"/> event of our Diviſions; how eagerly moſt men are carried to proſecute the deſignes of a Party, without regard to the Publike; how many croſſe Intereſts are proſecuted by oppoſite Parties in the State, which obſtruct all proceedings: How the Church is broken to peeces within it ſelf, and in the very Principles of a true ſettle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; how that which is called the preſent Church, is clogged and obſtructed in the way of Reformation, and in the aime and meanes to compaſſe it, is diſtant from the authority by which it is to be ſupported; dnd how that which ſeems to be eſtabliſhed, is ſet upon a ſandy foundation. If (I ſay) we look upon theſe things within, and then in reſpect of that which is without, we take notice of the diſtance at which we ſtand from the reſt of the beſt Reformed Churches, and of the Judgement which they make of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. (I ſay) if all this be laid together, as to Man; every one that hath eyes, muſt needs foreſee our inevitable ruine, if we continue thus; and that it is impoſſible for us to ſubſiſt long in this condition.</p>
            <p>Cleer it is, That if every one be left in his outward and publike wayes to the liberty of his own will, to croſſe and oppoſe his neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and affront him as he pleaſeth; that we ſhall need none other enemy to deſtroy us beſides our ſelves.</p>
            <p>But if now in the middeſt of our unſettlements, many enemies take their advantage to watch over us to cauſe us halt; if they blow dililigently the coals of our diviſions, ſupporting themſelves only with this hope, that the flame which is kindled amongſt us, will at laſt burne us up to aſhes, and that they may yet triumph over us therein; And if few do either obſerve their wayes to diſcover them, or endeavour by faithfull counſel to ſhut the door upon them; then we may infallibly conclude, that our deſolation will not only be certainly, but ſpeedily accompliſhed. And this is the danger wherein I conceive we all are at this time.</p>
            <p>Now before we can ſpeak of the Remedies, we muſt look a little into the Cauſes, whence theſe ſymptomes of our ruinous eſtate proceed.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not rake into all the particulars that might be obſerved,<note place="margin">Of the cauſes of our publike evils.</note> nor lay all the guilt upon any one: It is an eaſie matter to accuſe Adverſaries; and a very naturall courſe, to make ſuch as we do not love, odious unto others. But this is a way wherein narrow
<pb facs="tcp:160191:7"/> ſpirits walk; and men, as men, ſeeke rather to juſtifie themſelves before the world, then to reclaim with meekneſſe others from the error of their wayes before God. But I ſhall look to this laſt duty in the firſt place; and then let the other come as it may, if need be, that is, in caſe I find my ſelf ſuſpected or accuſed wrongfully. Nor ſhall I meddle with matters of State, to impute the cauſes of our miſery to the miſcarriages of Publike deſigns, or to the perverſnes of the counſels, or the wickednes of the Inſtruments thereof. It is no part of my calling, to trace Polititians in the crooked &amp; ſerpentine wayes wherein they walk. The Intereſt of States is a troubled Sea full of hideous Monſters, and hidden Rocks, whereupon the men of this world make ſhipwrack; and therein all the Nations and great Families of the earth are toſſed up and down according to the fancies of the Rulers, whoſe aime (though under other pretences) is nothing elſe but greatneſſe and command, to be ſupported by riches and power: My ſoule enter thou not into their counſel, for there is no truth in their wayes, there is no faithfulneſſe in their mouth, their inward part is very wickedneſſe: And that our diſtractions proceed from this generation of men, and from the Counſel, which are taken up upon their Principles, there is no queſtion to be made. But I ſhall leave them unto God, to be judged in his own time; And walking in mine own ſphere, ſhall ſpeake unto thee that art a Chriſtian indeed, of things belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our Religious profeſſion; to diſcover at the root the cauſes of our diſeaſe, which I conceive is nothing elſe but the corrupt Profeſſion of the true Religion, whereof we muſt all confeſſe our ſelves guilty, every one of us, more or leſſe: which how to Reform, firſt in our ſelves, and then in others, will be a profitable enquiry.</p>
            <p>If the Truth had not been manifeſted unto us, we ſhould have no ſinne; but now ſince we have known it, and held the profeſſion of it in unrighteouſneſſe, we have no cloak for our ſinne: we ought then to confeſſe and deplore that our profeſſion is corrupted, two wayes. Firſt, that moſt of us, although we are not ignorant of the Truth; yet we cannot deny but that we have loſt the true aime of the holy profeſſion thereof. Secondly, that although ſome aimes be right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet, and the profeſſion of many commendable; yet for the moſt part, the means and wayes of proſecuting the ſame, are either
<pb facs="tcp:160191:8"/> not anſwerable unto the Rules of Chriſtianity, or elſe directly deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive thereunto.</p>
            <p>The true aime of the Holy profeſſion is, to ſhew forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">What the aim of our profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is, and how we fail of it.</note> this evill world, the life and vertues of him who hath called us unto his Kingdome and glory. The Truth which we know, and which by the Goſpel is revealed unto us, is the teſtimony of Jeſus; that in him alone there is Redemption from all ſinnes; that by him alone there is all ſufficiencie of Grace to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved through Faith; that for his ſake alone wee have free ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe by the Spirit unto the Father; that the titles and names of King, Captain, and Forerunner, of Apoſtle, Prophet and High Prieſt, of Author and Finiſher of our ſalvation, do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to him alone: and that he being alone the Way, the Truth and the Life, no man can come to the Father but by him; this we do know and acknowledge; this wee doe maintaine and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe as the Truth: but who can ſay that the true aime of this profeſſion, is taken up and followed as it ought to be? this aime is to follow him as deare children, expreſſing him in his life, that is, in his lowly, juſt, holy, and unblameable converſation amongſt men; and in his death; that is, in his mortified, his ſelf-denying, his afflicted, his meeke and humble condition in this world. I ſay, this aime is not taken up and maintained in this profeſſion of the Truth; yet we know that this ſhould be our whole aime; and becauſe we know it, and doe it not, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our ſinne is heavy upon us; therefore theſe judgements doe overtake us, and God doth revenge the quarrel of his Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant againſt us; The Covenant is, that wee being in Chriſt<note place="margin">Matth. 16. 24. Rom. 8. 17. 2 Cor. 6, 17.</note> ſhall beare his Croſſe, and follow him; that we ſhall ſuffer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and be ſeparate from the world with him; and if wee touch not the uncleane things thereof, we have a promiſe that the Father will receive us. But who is it that doth truly aime at a full ſeparation from the world, and doth not intend to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the high things and full enjoyments thereof together with the profeſſion of the Truth? are we not content, and have we not a deſire to enjoy the faſhion of things preſent, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though wee know that we are called to ſeeke and apprehend one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the things to come? wee are called to be conformable unto the image of the Sonne of God; that is, to be no wayes confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable
<pb facs="tcp:160191:8"/> unto this world: but if we mind no ſuch thing, how can we be ſaid to maintaine the true aime of our holy profeſſion? The Socinians who have caſt off the Truth which is in Chriſt Jeſus concerning our Juſtification before God, and have made the acknowledgement of his Perſon in the Truth, void, by their Hereſies; theſe uphold ſtill the aime of the profeſſion, namely, that wee muſt follow his foot-ſteps: but wee who are convicted of the truth which they have denied, ſeeme to deny (at leaſt in our practiſe) that which they uphold; and conſequently make the truth it ſelfe which we acknowledge, ineffectuall, by our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion thereof; becauſe our aime is not in ſimplicity anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, but rather croſſe in all appearance unto the tenour of the new Covenant, and the end of our heavenly calling. Now if the maine and principall aime be loſt in our walking with God; how can he be at peace with us, or we with him? can two walke together except they be agreed? and are thoſe agreed whoſe aimes are different? doth not hee know the ſecrets of all hearts, that he may reward every one according to his works? what then can we expect from him other, then to reap the fruit of the ſeed which we ſowe? for we ſow to the fleſh worldly aimes in the field of a religious profeſſion; and can we expect any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther harveſt frrom thence but trouble and confuſion? This then is the firſt and maine cauſe of all our diſtractions, that the true aim of our Profeſſion is for the moſt part loſt amongſt us.</p>
            <p>The ſecond cauſe of our publike diſtraction is this; that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though for the maine, a worke of Reformation is truly aimed at by ſome; and many particular matters tending thereunto, are rightly deſigned by many, for the advancement of Religion: yet the meanes to bring this aime and theſe deſignes to paſſe, are not at all proportionate to the effect intended thereby. The work of Reformation (no doubt heartily aimed at by ſome) is a reall and thorough purging of the Church and State from the corruptions which have overgrowne the one and the other, and a ſettlement of both in a way of Righteouſneſſe: I ſay that<note place="margin">What the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation ai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at is, and why we come ſhort of it.</note> ſome aime heartily at this; and I truly doe beleeve it; but how many there are, God alone doth know. Sure I am wee cannot diſcerne very many, that have nothing elſe in their aime; but that moſt men, are very fierce in their private, and very cold
<pb facs="tcp:160191:9"/> in the publike occaſions, wee can eaſily diſcern; and yet their Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant both with God and man doth otherwiſe oblige them. And would to God there were not ſome that did make the aime of a Religious Reformation, a meere pretence to compaſſe their owne worldly ends: and a ſnare to entrap others into difficulties. I ſhall not meddle with the State, the Church is my taske at this time; but I finde, that to advance this Reformation in both, the meanes uſed are very diſproportionate to the effect, not only in reſpect of the way, wherein many of the Reformers walke in their own thoughts, but alſo in reſpect of their manner of concurrence eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one with another.</p>
            <p>The way wherein moſt men walke in their thoughts to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme the State, hath no relation unto Chriſtianity, but onely to the wiſdome of the world; and the way by which they ſeeke to reforme the Church, hath as little relation unto Charity, but is either carried in the way of Liberty, or of Authority; for men walke by one Rule of Prudencie in State matters, and by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other in Church affaires: as if a Chriſtion in his civill em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments might act without a Relation unto the will of Chriſt; or in Church-matters, might either pleaſe himſelf alone, without a relation to his Brethren, or might uſe all the power whereunto he can pretend, without a compliance and condeſcenſion to the weak. Theſe falſe Principles of Reformation, make men inconſiſtent with themſelves both in Church and State: here they act one way by this Rule, and there another way by that Rule, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times they jumble both wayes together, and look at once with two faces in the ſame buſineſſe different wayes. The ſimplicity and truth of Chriſtianity is by this meanes loſt in the Aim, and with it all true Prudencie in the Deliberation; and theſe two being gone, men are left unto the counſell of their own hearts, and betake themſelves in the execution of their deſignes, as well in the one as the other ſphere, to the tricks and contrivements of Policie, or to main power and ſtrength. And thus it falls out, that even the beſt and moſt hearty Reformers, walking as Men, in ſpirituall undertakings, fall into different wayes, take up different Maximes and Rules; and acting according to the ſame, (becauſe they reſpect not the Maximes and Rules of holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion in Chriſtianity) they make uſe of all their ſtrength and
<pb facs="tcp:160191:9"/> wit to oppoſe one another by different contrivements about the ſame work: And whiles they are wholly bent and poſſeſſed (as men naturally are) with the thoughts and affections of their own way and deſignment; they look upon others, no more as upon Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, but as upon a Party: Becauſe the ſimplicity of the Holy Profeſſion being loſt in the Aime, and the Rules of Holy Prudencie for the Communion of Saints, being laid aſide in the work; and men having forgotten that they are called to be Brethren, and members of one another, in their relation to Chriſt; they act no more in this, (though otherwiſe godly men, and hearty towards a Reformation) as men of godlineſſe, and truly reformed from the world, but as men intereſſed in a Party of the world; for ſuch or ſuch a Deſigne; to gain, or to oppoſe this or that Purpoſe. And becauſe this frame of ſpirit even in the beſt of us all (if we look not carefully to our ſpirits) may be found more or leſſe; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Meanes of our Reformation are diſproportionate unto the End for which they are undertaken; and this, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are not put forth by us in Gods way, which alone can edifie his Church, and without which no deſigne therein can proſper.</p>
            <p>Now when the Authours of our Reformation act thus, and are acted by a Principle of Diviſion within themſelves; how can they be brought to a hearty concurrence one with another, except a way can be found to rectifie this Fundamentall error in every one of them? And if the Inſtruments who are to put life in the Means of the Reformation, either cannot at all joyn, or if with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their conjunction nothing at all can be effected to any purpoſe for a ſettlement; how ſhall the work be carried on? If Chriſt would not have his own Nation to come to perfection without us; ſure he will not have any one of us come to perfection without another. If then the Agents who are to work out the Perfection whereat we aim, are ſo far from joyning in it, as that they prove by their conjunction rather deſtructive to one another, then fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers of Gods work; what hope is there of any ſucceſſe? Chriſtian Reader, give me leave without offence to ſpeak plainly what is obſerved in the Actors of a Reformation at this time, I mean ſuch who have the meanes thereof in their hand, or at leaſt a hand in the meanes: Theſe we may finde to be of three ſorts.
<pb facs="tcp:160191:10"/> Some minde the work ſincerely for it ſelf, although they now and then miſtake the Rules by which they ſhould walk; Some mind the work, only to gain ſome temporall advantages by it; And ſome minde it only to ſpie the faults, and ſtop the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings of the Actors. Now if our conſtitution be ſuch, that nothing can be done effectually in the Publike, without ſome of each ſort of theſe Agents, whenſoever they liſt to have a hand in the buſineſſe: it is apparent that no meanes can be imployed ſuccesfully towards the thorough Reformation of any thing. For the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright man failing (as we all do) to walk by his Rule (which is his ſtrength) he eaſily is drawn by the Worldling into a Plot, to do things for ſome End which is not anſwerable to the ſimplicity of the Goſpel; and aſſoon as any ſuch thing is in agitation, the third Agent, who is alſo intereſſed in State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contrivements, ſteps in to obſerve and obſtruct or overthrow their proceedings: And hence it is that the means of an intended Reformation, well meant by many, and ſet afoot by ſome, are unſuccesfull in the event, becauſe in the proceedings and uſe of Meanes there is no ſutableneſſe, but rather a deſtructive qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity unto the advancement of Religion. For in every thing that is propoſed or taken in hand, the jealouſie of a Party doth come in, which over-ruling the Affections by worldly conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, raiſeth an endleſſe conteſt about every thing concerning every part and circumſtance of the work; by which means the deſigne, though never ſo juſt and harmleſſe in it ſelf, is either ſtified in the conception, or elſe becomes abortive before the time of ſtrength; or a birth of ſo loug continuance, that in end there is no ſtrength left to bring it forth. And this is briefly my thought of the Cauſes why the main work of our Reformation is ſo much perplexed as we finde it. As for more particular matters honeſtly deſigned for the advancement of Religion, by many, in their ſeverall places and callings; As they can have but little influence upon the main, becauſe the great corner ſtones of the Reformation, are not as yet publikely profeſſed and laid, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which every one ſhould make an orderly ſuperſtructure of gold and ſilver and precious ſtones, in the unity of the ſpirit towards his Brethren: So, the more ſuch Deſignes are ſtood upon and advanced in a private courſe, they accidentally become the
<pb facs="tcp:160191:10"/> greater hinderances to the generall work; whiles men that are thereby ſtinted within themſelves, reſt ſatisfied in their own pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate wayes; and by leaving the thoughts of a publike Communion, they prove oppoſites thereunto; when they admit of nothing that is not every way agreeable unto their particular Contrivements.</p>
            <p>I am perſwaded that many able men throughout the Kingdome have many excellent things in readineſſe, which might be uſefully applied to the edification of the Churches, both for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Knowledge and of Godlineſſe, if the wayes of our Settlement were cleared. But now as matters ſtand, I cannot look otherwiſe upon their excellencies, but as upon the ſcattered ſtones of a building not yet framed, and as upon the furniture of a houſe whoſe model is neither apparent, nor yet well under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by any. Therefore although there be many men in theſe Churches of eminent abilities, and Veſſels of great honour, fit for very good uſes in the building of this Tabernacle: yet becauſe the Rule and way of their Brotherly communion and correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dencie is not determined as it ought to be, they ſtand (though in their private ſphere profitable as to God, yet) as to the Church uſeleſſe in the Communion of Saints. For the Parts of the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not being ſet together, their ſerviceable gifs are not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed as Joints ſhould be in the Body to make up and compact the whole: And for want of this aime and endeavour, by all that they do, they bring nothing forth unto perfection.</p>
            <p>I have briefly pointed at the Cauſes of our Diſeaſe; that thou mayeſt conſider thy ſelf (Chriſtian Reader) as in the preſence of God, how thou art led, by what ſpirit thou art guided, and how thou ſhouldeſt free thy ſelf from the guilt of contributing further any cauſe or matter of continuance to our Diſtempers. Now the Lord grant us all grace, to do all things without murmurings &amp; diſputings, to his glory, unblameably in Love. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am in the laſt place to ſpeak of the Remedies of this corrupt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the true Religion: And if I ſhould enter at large upon this task, I ſhould be obliged to write a Volume: but my purpoſe is only to name the Heads of things neceſſary to be intended and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, to advance our Reformation, and redreſſe the Evils which threaten our finall ruine; That if thou (Chriſtian Reader) art convicted of the uſefulneſſe thereof, thou mayeſt contribute in thy way what thou canſt thereunto.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:11"/>
            <p>The remedies then of our diſtracted condition I conceive will bee found in a diſcovery of two things, firſt of that which will helpe to rectifie the diſeaſe at the root, by taking away the cauſe which doth origionally beget it; Secondly of that which will helpe to prevent<note place="margin">Of the reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies of our pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blick diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note> the effects thereof; which become cauſes of increaſing the diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, to propagate and continue the diſeaſe.</p>
            <p>I have ſhewed my opinion that the cauſes which beget our diſtempers, are the want of the true aime in the holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and the diſproportionatnes of the meanes uſed to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the true and lawfull aimes of the Reformation which wee ſeeke to rectifie the inward Hypocriſie of the heart is only Gods worke; but to diſcover it and convict mens conſciences of it, may be the worke of his ſervants by the right interpretation and<note place="margin">The Remedie of the firſt cauſe of our diſeaſe.</note> application of the word, as the Apoſtle teſtifieth, <hi>1 Cor. 14.</hi> 24, 25. Yet the bare diſcovery of vice or error and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction of a naturall man that hee is guilty of it, is not enough to remedie the evill diſpoſition of his ſpirit or to beget a true aime in him to anſwer the heavenly call; nothing can doe this but God by the diſcovery of the truth in the lovelineſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; When hee giveth faith to the elect by the engrafted word, wherein they receive the love of the truth, which purifieth their ſoules, and maketh them obedient thereunto through the ſpirit: unto this worke of God the faithfull Miniſters of the Word are ſubſervient, when they hold forth the Truth in ſincerity and manifeſt the knowledge of the glory and life of God in the face of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The firſt remedy then, will bee to ſtirre up Miniſters, who underſtand this Myſtery of Godlineſſe ordinarily to preſſe and preach the maine things which diſcover the life and ſpirituall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of Chriſt as the Truth is in him, that their hearers may know, firſt, poſitively what that life is whereunto they are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; and then negatively, what that life and ſtate is wherein men are by nature from which they are called: and this ſhould bee done not ſo much by an inlargement of themſelves upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny particular branches and twigges of duties as upon the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the Principles and eſſentiall properties of the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall and carnall man, from whence the knowledge of duties will of it ſelfe flow: I doe not meane that the preaching of
<pb facs="tcp:160191:11"/> particular duties is unprofitable or ought to bee omitted; but I conceive that the fundamentals which diſcover the hidden man of the heart both in reſpect of the Righteouſneſſe of the ſpirituall and of the unrighteouſneſſe of the fleſhly nature ſhould be main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ordinarily ſo propoſed, as from the diſcovery of that which is conformable or inconformable unto the image of Gods life in Chriſt, all particular duties ſhould bee derived and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon the conſcience; and I beleeve that becauſe godly and zealous men commonly ſpend more of their ſtrength in matters of particular concernment then in ſuch a fundamentall courſe; that two evils ariſe from thence unto the hearers, and one in the Miniſters themſelves. Firſt, that the naturall corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the hearts of all men, remaine in ſome altogether, in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in a great meaſure undiſcovered at the root; by which means they ſtill conceiving well of themſelves, or better than they ought, are not truly humbled before God, and mortified unto the world, but live ſtill as men in the world, and take up the profeſſion of Religion in the performance of certain duties, rather than in the purſuit of a heavenly call to come unto Chriſt Jeſus. Secondly, that ſuch as are ingenuous and have taſted the Kingdome of God, and thereupon are gotten into a hatred of the world, being fervent in ſpirit to ſerve the Lord, are driven, by the much preſſing of particular duties, to an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver acting zeale; either againſt or for ſome perſons or actions, which zeale having no temperament of love, meekneſſe, and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, to heale and beare with the infirmities of the weake, or to bring their owne proceeding with them home to the true aime of the holy profeſſion which is to diſcover Chriſt unto thoſe that goe aſtary from him, they are ſo farre from edifying the Church of God by their forwardneſſe, that they rather diſturb and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy every thing they meddle withall; but if they were inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by their teachers to underſtand the way wherein Chriſt did<note place="margin">Mat. 12. 19, 20.</note> walke to ſhew judgement unto the Gentiles; namely, <hi>that he did not ſtrive, nor cry, nor cauſe any man heare his voyce in the ſtreets: that hee did not break the bruiſed reed, nor quench the ſmoking flax till hee ſend forth judgement unto victory.</hi> If I ſay they were taught to know him in this, as in all other things, and were obliged to judge themſelves in all their
<pb facs="tcp:160191:12"/> aimes, to doe nothing out of the way of conformity unto him, in his walking in the fleſh, they would eaſily refrain from the intemperancy of their paſſionate zeal, for or againſt particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar matters which reach not unto the heart of the profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>The evill which in this courſe of preaching doth befall unto the Miniſters themſelves, who otherwiſe are Godly and holy men, is this; that they eaſily overſhoot themſelves, either by preſſing a particular duty too much and indiſcreetly laying too great weight upon it towards all without diſtinction of caſes, whereby the weaker conſciences are ſtraitned and enſnared; or by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a duty unto matters of ſtate and publick relations to the prejudice of one party for the advantage of another upon reports or miſtakes and miſconſtructions of matters, from whence oft times great ſcandals and diſcontents ariſe, and are fomented to the widening of breaches without all hope of reconcilement: If the Miniſters preſſe not the fundamentall aime of the profeſſion; but reſt in the delivery of theoreticall truths, and the application thereof unto particular duties, It is no great wonder that their hearers remain ignorant of it, and walke not up to it; and it muſt naturally follow, that all the care whereunto their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence will draw them in their profeſſion, will bee nothing elſe, but a profeſſsion of ſome particular tenets and practiſes for which they will ſtrive as for life and death: not that I think that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny truth or righteous practiſe is rightly to be eſteemed or neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected; but that all the Theorie of the world, and all the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances that can be wrought in particular duties may bee a matter of meere Hypocriſie in the profeſſor; and nothing elſe but an occaſion of ſtrife and diſturbance towards thoſe to whom our profeſſion is addreſſed, if the true aime of the holy profeſſion bee not minded: the teaching then of the aime of our profeſſion (by Gods bleſſing upon the word of his ſervants) may rectifie the purpoſe of the hearers in their profeſſion, and cure the firſt and fundamentall cauſe of all our diſtempers; and if once this radicall cauſe be taken away, the ſecundary which is but a ſtreame flowing from that fountain, will ſoon be dried up, by the heat of true love and ſincerity which will take poſſeſſion of the affections of thoſe that in the Spirit follow Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:12"/>
            <p>For as the ſecond Cauſe of our Diſtempers, <hi>viz.</hi> the want of<note place="margin">The Remedy of the ſecond Cauſe of our Diſeaſe.</note> Proportion in the Means uſed towards a through Reformation, to produce the Effect intended thereby, is an effect of the firſt: So the ſecond Remedy of that evil, will be a conſequence of the firſt, namely the way of doing all things in love. For he that aimeth at nothing in the way of his Profeſſion, but to follow Jeſus Chriſt, will find that he in his way of walking did proportionate all his undertakings to the end for which he did them, by the manifeſtation of Gods love to thoſe towards whom he did make his application. And becauſe there is little or no ſincerity of Brotherly love apparent in the uſe of the Means which are ſet a foot for the advancement of a Religious Reformation amongſt us; therefore every thing which is done by many of us, is altogether unſutable to the end for which it is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed: for although the thing which is done, be in it ſelf ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo good and juſt; yet if the ſpirit of Divine love do not go along with the performance of the work there will be no proportion found therein to reach the end for which it is to be undertaken; becauſe there is nothing but love that can fit every thing to the good of thoſe to whom it is done. The Apoſtle ſaith, that there is <hi>neither circumciſion available in Chriſt Jeſus, nor uncircumciſion, but</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Faith which worketh by Love:</hi> The object of Faith is Chriſt, when we take him in the Covenant as our aime to be found in him: and if this Faith hath any life in us, and is not a meer verball pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, it will be operative in that Love wherein He did all his works amongſt men, and towards his Father. The Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Rule by which we ſhould walk as children of God, giveth us this charge, <hi>Epheſ. 5. 2. Walk</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>in love, as Chriſt alſo hath loved us and hath given himſelf for us.</hi> If then our aime is Chriſt, it will appeare that the chief thing wherein our conformity with Chriſt muſt ſtand, will be the exerciſe of love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Brethren for Gods ſake, and of Holineſſe to be ſeparate from the world; and when we ſhall reflect upon the uſe of the Means which are ſet afoot and put in the hands of moſt men for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of our Reformation, we ſhall find that nothing is ſo much wanting both in the framing of the counſels, and in the execution of the works, as the ſpirit of Brotherly love, and of Holineſſe: and where theſe two are deficient in thoſe who act a Reformation, what can the event be other then diſorder and confuſion?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:13"/>
            <p>Some Act altogether by the way and in the means of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian liberty, ſome by the way and in the means of Chriſtian Authority; but becauſe neither of theſe for the moſt part are acted by the ſpirit of love to one another, or by the ſpirit of Holineſſe to bee ſeperate from the world, and from their owne intereſts in what they doe; therefore they act nothing for, but againſt one another, as if Chriſtian Liberty and Chriſtian Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority were things altogether inconſiſtent; and ſo the means which ſhould advance both the one and the other part of our ſpirituall conſtitution, are not only ineffectuall, but offenſive and deſtructive to each other, becauſe neither the deſire of liberty, nor the pretence of Authority are put forth in the ſpirit of love, to ſerve others thereby in true Holineſſe, but a certain intereſt of ſtate is rather look't upon both wayes, which makes both the path of Liberty and of Authority to become unchriſtian to thoſe that walke therein with partiality and worldly aimes, and this is the only cauſe why all our works and proceedings of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture doe miſcarry; becauſe many of thoſe that are the Actors thereof in making uſe of the means doe not, for the moſt part minde the golden Rules of ſpirituall proportion and prudency for edification, which are the lawes of Love and Holineſſe; but in ſtead of theſe are carried ſometimes, even in their beſt actions, by a Rule of humane Jealouſie, which begets nothing but Paſſion and Policie: And this once being diſcovered, doth wholly blaſt their proceeding, and maketh all the means, though otherwiſe in themſelves never ſo powerfull, wholly diſproportionate unto the effect.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Remedy then is this: That godly Miniſters, whom I look upon as the chiefe Actors of our Reformation, and ſuch as muſt put life into the Meanes thereof, muſt firſt ſet their own hearts aright in this frame of Love and Holineſſe, and then ſtirre up one another to the Counſels and Deliberations which theſe Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, according to the Word of GOD, will ſuggeſt. And becauſe in the framing of Deſignes which tend unto a publike good, it is apparent that on all ſides a Concurrence is ſought for by thoſe that act in the affaires of State, with thoſe that are ſet in the Church to act for Chriſts kingdome: and that as <hi>Moſes</hi> could not be without <hi>Aaron</hi> at firſt, when he came to the people;
<pb facs="tcp:160191:13"/> So <hi>Aaron</hi> could not be without <hi>Moſes</hi> at laſt when the people was to march through the Wilderneſſe; and that neither the one nor the other durſt go a ſtep forward without a direction from God in their wayes; therefore in the concurrence of States-men and Miniſters towards a Reformation by the uſe of the meanes; both <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> muſt walke by one Rule of Chriſtianity, whereof the end is brotherly love and holineſſe, and not by two different rules, as the cuſtome of moſt men is, and if the Miniſters ſuffer themſelves to be taken off from this aime by any pretence whatſoever, or doe not labour to ſway the Reſolutions of the Maſter-Builders in the common wealth, according to theſe Rules, that all publick conſtitutions and the wayes of acting them upon the ſpirits of men may ſavour of nothing but of love, of holineſſe, and of meekneſſe in Authority by the directions of the word and the way of Chriſts walking; (I ſay) if Miniſters do not exactly keep themſelves to this Rule and draw others to walk thereby, they will be by their owne weakneſſe and the craft of others drawn over to ſerve ſtate ends, and be made uſe of to divide others, and to be divided from others and from one another amongſt themſelvs, according to the wicked maxim of Machiavilian Government <hi>Divide &amp; Impera,</hi> and who doth not ſee that the enimies of our Reformation, leave nothing unattempted to put this maxime in execution, and that they find opportunity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough and more then enough, ſo to doe in every thing which is at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted in publick by reaſon of the unchriſtian frame of our Spirit and our walking by a two-fold Rule or without the Rules of charity and holineſſe? For Satan which worketh in them, and is the Prince of this world, finding us who pretend to bee Miniſters of Chriſt out of the Sphere of Chriſts walking, and in the Sphere of his owne Kingdome, medling with worldly intereſts which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne us not, hath power over us, to make us that are called Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters more then all other men in the world to ſerve his ends, of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbing the Peace of mankind, and tearing the Church of God in Peices, and only becauſe wee are not in the way wherein God hath ſet us: but if on the otherſide wee ſtand in the ſimplicity of our Chriſtian way and walking to deliberate and doe all things both in private and publick by love, and for holineſſe according to Chriſts example, then wee are in our full ſtrength, armed with light, and
<pb facs="tcp:160191:14"/> Satan in the power of darkneſſe cannot come neer us or comprehend us. And if it is not poſsible through our own default to put this Counſell in practiſe amongſt us, who are convicted of the truth thereof, whether we are Independents or Preſbyterians, we are all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like guilty before God of our own ruine, and of the generall diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance of this Church and State.</p>
            <p>I have ſpoken as briefly as I could contract my thoughts concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note place="margin">The Remedy of the evil ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of our diſeaſe.</note> the Remedies which will worke a cure upon the Cauſes of our diſeaſe; now I muſt ſpeake alſo a word of that which I conceive will bee of uſe to prevent the dangerous effects thereof, whereby our diſtempers are daily increaſed. The diſeaſe, in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, is a diſtractedneſſe of ſpirit in a divided minde, which hath wrought a diſ-joynting of our affections; ſo that we ſtand as a tall man diſtracted in his thoughts, and divided in all his reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, who hath no command or little uſe of any of his members; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are all out of joynt, and hang as it were looſe one from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. Thus this Church the talleſt of any Reformed in Europe, and fit to bee a leader of the reſt in the ſpirituall Conqueſt of <hi>Canaan,</hi> doth ſtand within it ſelfe and to others uſeleſſe.</p>
            <p>The effects of this our diſtraction and diviſion which increaſe our diſeaſe and make it grow upon us, are chiefely three. Frſt jealouſies, fears and evill ſurmiſes of every thing that is deſigned by any party which is not our own. Secondly, cenſures, reproa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches diſputes, accuſations and revilings againſt the perſons and the actions of a different party. Thirdly, oppoſitions and croſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings in counſells and attempts, againſt all that are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly in the way wherein that party doth walke of which we are. Theſe three effects beget each other reciprocally not only in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man within himſelfe, and in every party within it ſelfe; but in every man and party in relation to another, as hee ſtands at a diſtance from the ſame; and all of theſe make our diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers almoſt paſt remedy, nor can the one well bee cured with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other; and therefore the Remedies muſt needs bee ſuch, as can have an influence upon all at once, to ſtop the current thereof, upon our own and other mens ſpirits, if they ſhould prove ſuccesfull towards a cure.</p>
            <p>The field of this diſcourſe is ſo large, that I ſhall at this time
<pb facs="tcp:160191:14"/> but name only the heads of things, which muſt become the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredients of this Phyſick; leaving the particular compoſition and application thereof unto ſome other time, wherein God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may give a call and grace to elaborate the ſame; and this I ſhall do to give unto thee Chriſtian Reader, an object of prayer and meditation; that thou mayeſt be moved to goe to God, and to ſtirre up thy ſelfe and others daily, till theſe Remedies be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed unto our diſeaſes as they ought to be.</p>
            <p>If then the forenamed effects of our diſeaſed Church ſhould bee cured by this worke of Reformation; wee muſt conſider not only what is requiſite to allay our preſent fits of diſtemper; but alſo that which both in our age and in time to come will build us up unto a habitation of God through the ſpirit, and propagate the bleſſings of the Goſpel unto Poſterity.</p>
            <p>To cure then our preſent diſtempers, it is evident that an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited liberty to every one to vent and practiſe whatſoever he ſhall think good without controll, will not do it; becauſe this very Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty hath begotten our diſtempers, and no doubt will increaſe them, if no courſe be found to regulate mens proceedings concerning their publike Profeſſion, ſo as they ſhall have no juſt cauſe to complain that they are perſecuted for Conſcience ſake. But how to determine the way of Regulating mens proceedings, ſo as none ſhall have any juſt cauſe of complaint, herein lies the difficulty: Yet I conceive it may thus be taken away: Let all Parties who take the Holy Scriptures for the Rule of Faith and Practiſe, ſet down poſitively and declare plainly, either that which they judge to be fundamentall in matter of Doctrine and Practiſe, or clearly commanded and uſefull for Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; or that wherein they profeſſe a full agreement with their Brethren. If they do either of the two last, as (I thinke) all may eaſily be engaged to do, either by the demand of any one Party, that ſeeks to advance Peace; or by the command of the Civil Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, who ought to reſtrain Quarrels, and take away the cauſes thereof ſo far as he can in publike: If (I ſay) either of theſe po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Declarations, or both, be delivered by each Party to another, then the Apoſtles counſel is to be put in execution, which is <hi>Phil. 3. 16, Whereunto we have already attained, let us walk by the ſame rule, let us minde the ſame thing.</hi> Which counſel, to me, doth furniſh this matter of adviſe, in reference to our preſent con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:15"/>
            <p>Firſt, let the Parties by ſome of their ſelected men (who ſhall do all things with their full conſent and knowledge) make a draught of the full Agreement of thoſe former Declarations; and that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing imparted unto all, let an Acknowledgement be made concerning it, that it is that whereunto All have attained, and wherein they will minde the ſame thing to edifie one another in the Truth where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they are come.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let the ſame Parties declare negatively the things wherein they conceive they diſagree from each other: And when theſe Declarations are drawn up, let thoſe that have penned them adde their advice concerning the wayes of reconciling the differences, whether in Judgement or in Practiſe; and then let ſome ſelected men, the moſt moderate of each Party, be called together to ſet down the joint agreement of their Advices concerning the way of recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling Differences; and according to that Agreement, let them make a tryall of reconciling the Differences, and offer it to all, only as an Eſſay without prejudice to any, to be conſidered.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let the ſame Parties declare, both Poſitively and Negatively, the Rules by which they are willing to walk inoffen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively towards thoſe with whom they do not agree; and in caſe any offences be given or taken about thoſe things, How the ſame ought to be taken away by mutuall conſent. Here then the ſame ſelected men, or others, may be ſet a work to peruſe ſuch Declarations, and gather into one Body the Rules whereunto all ſides will agree to walk by, to avoid offences; and let every one who will pretend to any freedome of Profeſſion in publike, be obliged towards thoſe that have inſpection over the publike, to walke by thoſe Rules of inoffenſiveneſſe, notwithſtanding any difference that is, or may ariſe in after-times amongſt themſelves or others.</p>
            <p>Theſe things I conceive may be done without great difficulty, and will be done by all thoſe that love peace; And that they may be done, I could wiſh that the Supreme Authority of the Kingdom would appeare in it to procure it; that when the Publike <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> and <hi>Catechiſme,</hi> ſhall be put forth, all ſuch as ſhall deſire the protection of the Supreme Power, and ſhall be willing to live in peace with thoſe that allow of the Government eſtabliſhed by Law, may be enjoyned thus to proceed towards the ſettlement of an union between them and their Brethren, in the Profeſſion of the Goſpel:
<pb facs="tcp:160191:15"/> and in the mean while, till this can be done, if all ſides would agree voluntarily upon a ceſſation from all bitterneſſe and railing accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations againſt each other, or if it ſhould by thoſe that are in place of Authority be enjoyned as a Preparatory for ſo good a worke, it would be very conſonant to the abatement of our diſtractions, and commendable in thoſe that ſhould do it willingly. But if no ſuch way of tranſacting differences can be brought to paſſe anſwerable to the counſel of the Apoſtle, truly then I muſt confeſſe that I can ſee no way to prevent the growing effects of our fatall diſtempers, except God ſo bleſſe the Government by law eſtabliſhed, with that ſpirit of Diſcretion, of Moderation, of Equity, and of Lowlineſſe in all things which it doth act, that none ſhall be able to find any juſt grievance at it. And to this effect, the leſſe the Claſſicall Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byteries ſhall reſemble the Civil Courts of Judicature, or the Biſhops Courts in former time, the more they will be ſutable to the end for which they are inſtituted, which is, to entertain Brotherly confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences and conſultations about ſpirituall matters for mutuall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance and ſupport in the wayes of God; and not at all to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with the Congregations in any of their particular affairs, which are not voluntarily brought unto them as a Caſe wherein their Judgement is ſought unto; for no particular Church, by its ſubordination to a Claſſis, is to be deprived of any right which it hath within it ſelf, but is rather thereby to be maintained therein.</p>
            <p>The Maximes then of ſpirituall Communion to be obſerved in the Claſſical Presbyteries, that all miſconſtructions of their wayes which occaſion jealouſies and clamours, may be prevented, ought to be publiſhed, to wipe away the fears which enſuare us into diſtractions againſt the duties of Love. And it will be neceſſary not only to publiſh thoſe Maximes for this end; but three other things more muſt be ſatisfactorily, and from the grounds of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture cleared, if ever the Government ſhall proſper, to ſettle us in Peace.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be made out, that the Miniſters of particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, and their Elderſhips, are bound in conſcience in the things belonging to their charge, to maintain a Brotherly communion and correſpondencie with each other, and conſequently to enter into ſuch combinations as to that effect they can conveniently caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb facs="tcp:160191:16"/>2. That to ſuch Combinations of Elderſhips, Appeals may and ought to be made, hath ſufficiently been cleared by many, &amp; eſpecially by Mr. <hi>Paget</hi> of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> in a Treaty which hath not been an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by any that I know. But the ſecond thing requiſite to clear mens ſcrupulous apprehenſions about the proceedings of ſuch com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bined Elderſhips, is not ſo much their Right to receive Appeals and judge Authoritatively thereof; as to make the wayes of their hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling matters in judging thereof, as a Senate of ſpirituall men, evident; that is, To ſhew forth their way of handling things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, by what Rules and Grounds it doth ſtand, in the Communion of Saints; to prejudge no mans juſt and conſcionable Liberty, and yet to act Regularly, and with all competent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority.</p>
            <p n="3">3. What the way ſhould be, by which the Combination of Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ought to deale with ſuch as are without, who diſturbe and trouble the peace of their Congregations. Here, the manner of conferring with thoſe that are not co-ordinate with them in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, is to be opened, to ſhew that it doth tend only to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction and reformation of mens ſpirits, and not to the blaſting of mens names, or any other outward inconveniencie to be brought upon them by reaſon of their diſagreement from them in opinion and practiſe.</p>
            <p>If theſe declarations concerning the Claſſical Preſbyteries were publiſhed, as I conceive they may bee drawn up, from the grounds of Scripture, and undeniable Principles of Holy commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and right reaſon; and backed with the practiſe of all the beſt Reformed Churches; they might bee a fit playſter for the ſores which are in mens minds againſt the government.</p>
            <p>Theſe are in briefe the heads of my thoughts concerning the cure of our preſent fits of diſtemper, as it may by Gods bleſſing be wrought out in a ſpirituall way; what the Civill Magiſtrate in his Prudence and according to his place, may and ought to doe outwardly to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the outward behaviours of men, ſo as to make them without offence, I ſhall not now ſpeak of; but leave it to the wiſdome of the State; praying, that God would direct them to doe all things by their own light and for their true end of government; and not by the inſtigation and prompting of others who may have by-ends to ſway them.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:16"/>
            <p>As for the Reformation in times to come (becauſe wee ſhould endevour not only to build up the waſt places, but alſo to lay the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of many generations) thoughts ſhould be had of theſe things following; without the accompliſhment of which in ſome competent meaſure, we ſhall tranſmit little or no comfort unto poſterity in the fruit of our undertakings. Thoughts then I ſay ſhould be had,</p>
            <p>Firſt, of the wayes of conſtituting Schooles for the education of youth throughout the Kingdome in reference to foure ſorts of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. <hi>viz. 1.</hi> to the Mechanicks. 2. To the Gentry and Nobles. 3. To thoſe that are to be trained up to teach others in humane Sciences. 4. To the ſons of the Prophets.</p>
            <p>Secondly, of the wayes of purging the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities from the froth of ambitious and contentious Learning, and Debates of Sciences falſly ſo called; To bring Scholars to a Demonſtrative way of at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining profitable Knowledge, and by the exerciſe and imployment of their Talents for the benefit of each other without envy, to increaſe <hi>in infinitum</hi> beyond the preſent bounds thereof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, of enlarging unto all ſorts of people Scripturall know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; not only by Catecheticall exerciſes, more exactly to be intended for the manner thereof, by Paſtors, Parents, School-maſters, and Maſters of families, then hitherto hath been minded; but by regular and well ordered Conferences, either in private or in publike, as well to reſolve doubts from the Text, as to enlarge the diſcovery of Truths and Myſteries therein.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, of the wayes and Rules of Spirituall and Rationall Meditation, in Divine and Humane things; to rectifie the Principles of mens thoughts in the ſearch of Knowledge; whether from the Scripture, by the grounds of demonſtrating the true ſenſe thereof, in the Literal, Material, and Myſtical analyſis of the Text; or from other Objects wherein the Mind of man may be more freely imployed, either for Theoretical or Practical aims.</p>
            <p>Of all which it is not now ſeaſonable to ſpeak any more, but this; That I ſhall intreat thee (good Reader) not to deſpiſe the dayes of ſmall things, nor to miſtruſt Gods power and goodneſſe concerning that which he doth intend to do in the laſt dayes; but to lift up thy prayer with me, that we may be all fitted to receive, and to make right uſe of the Grace, which in the midſt of many trials is offered unto us in Chriſt Jeſus. To him be glory for ever. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:160191:17"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 1. Pag. 1.</hi> COncerning a Church as it is the houſe of God.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 2. p. 2.</hi> Of the Members of Chriſts body, and their Conjunction.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 3. p. 4.</hi> Of the Ordinances of Worſhip and Government.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 4. p. 7.</hi> Concerning the office &amp; imployment of the Paſtor &amp; Teacher.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 5. p. 19.</hi> Concerning the office and imployment of Ruling Elders.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 6. p. 23.</hi> Some Rules taken from the Word of God, to ſhew how the Elderſhips of a particular Church ought to ſettle the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Government of the Flock committed to them.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 7. p. 25.</hi> Concerning the office and imployment of Deacons.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 8. p. 28.</hi> Concerning the duty of Chriſtians, as they are to be in a particular Church, and under the government of Rulers ſet over them in the Lord.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 9. p. 36.</hi> Certain Rules concerning the Adminiſtration of the Lords Supper, for the decent ordering of the action, offered to the conſideration of thoſe that ſcruple at the geſture of Sitting.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Chap. 10. p. 55.</hi> The practiſe of the beſt Reformed Churches, in the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Lords ſupper.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:160191:17"/>
            <head>THE GROUNDS OF THE SPIRITUAL FRAME OF THE HOUSE of GOD.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> Concerning a <hi>CHURCH</hi> as it is the Houſe of God.</head>
               <p>1. <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> Congregationall Church is a (<hi>a</hi>) dwelling place of Mount <hi>Zion, (a</hi>) Iſa. 4, 5. <hi>The Lord will create a cloud upon every dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing place of Mount</hi> Zion, <hi>and upon her Aſſemblies. Ergo,</hi> there are many dwelling places, &amp; many Aſſemblies of Mount <hi>Zion:</hi> and each of them hath a promiſe of the Lords preſence with them.] And one of her Aſſemblies, that is to ſay, a (<hi>b</hi>) Houſe of God. (<hi>b</hi>) 1 Tim. 3. 15. <hi>The Houſe of God, which is the Church of the living God.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:160191:18"/>
               <p>2. This houſe is <hi>built upon the foundation (c) of the Apoſtles and Prophets; Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the cheife corner ſtone.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>(<hi>c</hi>) Epheſ. 2. 20. <hi>and ye</hi> (viz. Epheſians) <hi>are built upon the foundation of the Apoſtles and Prophets; Jeſus Chriſt himſelf be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the cheif corner ſtone,</hi> as the Epheſians were, ſo all true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are built upon Chriſt alone.</p>
               <p>3. The end and uſe of this building, is to bee an (<hi>d</hi>) habitation of God through the Spirit. (<hi>d</hi>) Epheſ. 2. 22. <hi>in whom you</hi> (viz. Epheſians) <hi>alſo are builded together, for an habitation of God through the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. God then through (<hi>e</hi>) Chriſt dwelleth therein; (<hi>e</hi>) Joh. 17. 23. <hi>I in them, and thou in me; that they may be made perfect in one. Ergo,</hi> if they be united by any other tye to one another, then by their relation to Chriſt, they are neither perfect as one; nor a true habitation of God by the Spirit.</p>
               <p>And that two wayes:</p>
               <p>Firſt in the lively members of Chriſts body fitly joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               <p>Secondly in the ſpirituall ordinances of his worſhip and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment rightly obſerved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> Of the Members of Chriſts body and their conjunction.</head>
               <p>THe members of Chriſts body are all the lively (<hi>f</hi>) ſtones of the houſe of God, (<hi>f</hi>) 1 Pet. 2. 4, 5. <hi>To whom coming as unto a living ſtone, &amp;c. ye alſo as lively ſtones are built up a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall houſe, an holy Prieſthood, to offer up ſpirituall ſacrifice acceptable to God, by Jeſus Chriſt</hi>] built upon (<hi>g</hi>) Chriſt; and ſet in their proper places, to offer up ſpirituall ſacrifice unto him. (<hi>g</hi>) 1 Cor. 3. 9. <hi>Ye are Gods building;</hi> and Epheſ. 2. 21. <hi>In whom</hi> (viz. in Chriſt) <hi>all the building is fitly framed together.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. The ſtones of this building are either the Foundations, of the Corners, or the Walls.</p>
               <p>3. The chief and only foundation, which is the head of the corner, is Chriſt Jeſus. 1 Cor. 3. 11. <hi>Other foundation can no man lay, then that is laid, which is Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> &amp; 1 Pet. 2. 7.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:160191:18"/> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you he is precious (viz.</hi> Chriſt) <hi>but unto the diſobedient,</hi> the <hi>ſtone which the builders diſallowed, the ſame is made the head of the corner.</hi> Compared with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. 22. &amp; Iſa. 28. 16. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, behold I lay in Sion for a foundation a ſtone, a tried ſtone, a precious corner-ſtone, a ſure foundation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. The ſecondary foundations (<hi>i</hi>) next unto Chriſt, are the Apoſtles and Prophets, (<hi>i</hi>) Epheſ. 2. 20. <hi>Built upon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Apoſtles and Prophets, Jeſus Chriſt himſelf being the chief corner-ſtone.</hi> &amp; Revel. 21. 14. <hi>And the wall of the city had twelve foundations, and in them the names of the twelve Apoſtles of the Lambe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. The walls are the Body of common members, which is the Congregation of believers, joyned (<hi>k</hi>) together in one. (<hi>k</hi>) Cant. 8. 8, 9. <hi>We have a little ſiſter,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>What ſhall we do for our ſiſter?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>If ſhe be a wall, we ſhall build upon her a palace of ſilver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. The corner-ſtones which joyn the walls together, are Officers (<hi>l</hi>) in the houſe, (<hi>l</hi>) Epheſ. 4. 11, 12. <hi>Paſtors and teachers, for the perfecting of the Saints,</hi> and (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>for the making up</hi>) And as (<hi>m</hi>) joynts in the members of the Body. (<hi>m</hi>) Ibid. verſ. 16. From <hi>whom the whole body fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplieth. Ergo,</hi> the joyning and compacting of the Body together, is by the office of the joynts.</p>
               <p>7. Theſe officers are differenced (<hi>n</hi>) according to the grace and gifts given to them for the edification of the Body, (<hi>n</hi>) Rom. 12. 6. <hi>Having then gifts differing, according to the grace that is given us.</hi> &amp; Epheſ. 4. 16. That <hi>which every joynt ſupplieth—maketh increaſe of the Body unto the edifying of it ſelf in love.</hi>] in their proper (<hi>o</hi>) offices. (<hi>o</hi>) Rom. 12. 4. <hi>All mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers have not the ſame office.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>8. Theſe offices are either for ſpeaking, (<hi>p</hi>) or for the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome ſervice. (<hi>p</hi>) 1 Pet. 4. 11. <hi>If any man ſpeak—if any man miniſter,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) that is, doth ſervice.</p>
               <p>The office of him that ſpeaketh, is either to teach, (<hi>q</hi>) or to exhort. (<hi>q</hi>) Rom. 12. 7, 8. <hi>He that teacheth, on teaching; he that exhorteth, on exhortation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The office of him that is imployed about ſome ſervice, is either
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:160191:19"/> to rule, <hi>(r)</hi> or to impart and ſhew mercy. <hi>(r)</hi> Rom. 12. 8. <hi>He that ruleth—he that ſheweth mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>9. By theſe offices, all things neceſſary and comfortable to the houſhold of Faith, in reſpect of the inward and outward man, may be ſupplied.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the inward man, it is neceſſary that the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the houſhold be ſupplied with knowledge, and the will with ſincerity of zeale to obedience. The firſt belongeth to the Teacher, the ſecond to the Exhorter.</p>
               <p>In reſpect of the outward man, it is neceſſary that the life and converſation of the houſhold be rightly ordered, that is, ſutably <hi>(s)</hi> to the holy profeſſion. <hi>(s)</hi> Epheſ. 4. 1. <hi>Walke worthy of the vocation wherewith ye are called</hi>] And that their bodily ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities be ſupplied in caſe of want, by the charity of their fellow members. The firſt belongeth unto the Ruler; the ſecond unto the Deacon.</p>
               <p>10. More then this nothing is requiſite in ordinary, to build up the Body in <hi>(t)</hi> love within it ſelf. <hi>(t)</hi> Epheſ. 4. 16. <hi>The effectuall working in the meaſure of every part, maketh increaſe of the Body unto the edifying of it ſelf in love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore, in ordinary, none other offices are either uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, or mentioned in the Scriptures, as appointed by Chriſt for the conſtitution of his Church.</p>
               <p>The life <hi>(u)</hi> and action of theſe members, is to obſerve all Gods ordinances. <hi>(u)</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 2. <hi>I praiſe you brethren—that you keep the ordinances as I delivered them to you.</hi> &amp; Luk. 1. 6. <hi>They were Righteous before God, walking in all the commandements and ordinances of the Lord blameleſſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Of the Ordinances of Worſhip and Government.</head>
               <p>1. THe ordinances of Gods worſhip are duties preſcribed in the <hi>(x)</hi> Word, <hi>(x)</hi> Iſa. 8. 20. <hi>To the law and to the teſtimony.</hi> &amp; chap. 66. 1, 2. <hi>The heaven is my throne—but to this man will I look, who trembleth at my word.</hi>] According to which God is to be ſerved in ſpirit <hi>(y)</hi> and truth, by every
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:160191:19"/> one. <hi>(y)</hi> Joh. 4. 24. <hi>God is a Spirit, and they that worſhip him, muſt worſhip him in ſpirit and in truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And the ordinances of Government are duties preſcribed for ever unto the <hi>(z)</hi> Rulers, <hi>(z)</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 15. <hi>That thou mayeſt know how thou oughteſt to behave thy ſelf in the houſe of God.</hi> &amp; chap. 5. 21. <hi>I charge thee before God, and the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the elect Angels, that thou obſerve theſe things, without preferring one before another, doing nothing by partiality.</hi> &amp; chap. 6. 13, 14. <hi>I give thee charge in the ſight of God,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>that thou keep this commandement without ſpot unrebukeable, untill the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>] According to which the affairs of the houſhold are to be <hi>(a)</hi> ordered, <hi>(a)</hi> Tit. 1. 5. <hi>I left thee in Crete, that thou ſhouldeſt ſet, in order the things that are wanting—as I had appointed thee.</hi> &amp; 1 Cor. 14. 40. <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order.</hi> &amp; Coloſſ. 2. 5. <hi>I am with you in the ſpirit, joying and beholding your order.</hi>] both for the increaſe <hi>(b)</hi> of Grace, <hi>(b)</hi> Epheſ. 4. 13. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill we all come unto a perfect man.</hi> And <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>maketh increaſe.</hi>] and the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of <hi>(c)</hi> Scandals, <hi>(c)</hi> 1 Cor. 5. 7. <hi>Purge out the old leaven.</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 12. Do not ye judge them that are within?</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 13. Therefore put away from among you that wicked perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. The uſe of theſe Ordinances; is, to betroth <hi>(d)</hi> the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of men, and bind them over unto God in the covenant of grace; and to keep them faithfull to him, <hi>(d)</hi> Ezech. 16. <hi>v.</hi> 8. till 15. &amp; 2 Cor. 11. 2. <hi>I have eſpouſed you to one husband, that I may preſent you as a chaſte Virgin to Chriſt.</hi>] or to reclaim them <hi>(e)</hi> when they are faulty therein. <hi>(e)</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 21. <hi>Shall I come unto you with a rod,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>3. All the Ordinances then are Meanes which God doth uſe, either to bring <hi>(f)</hi> men to his Covenant, <hi>(f)</hi> Exod. 19. 5. <hi>If ye will obey my voice indeed, and keep my covenant, then ye ſhall be peculiar treaſure unto me.</hi>] or to confirm <hi>(g)</hi> and keep them in it, <hi>(g)</hi> Iſa. 8. 16. <hi>Binde up the Teſtimony, ſeal the Law among my diſciples.</hi> &amp; Ezek. 20. 19, 20. <hi>I am the Lord your God; walk in my ſtatutes, and keep my judgements and do them; and hallow my Sabbaths; and they ſhall be a ſigne between me and you,</hi> that <hi>ye may know that I am the Lord your God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. The meanes which doth bring men to the Covenant, is that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:160191:20"/> which begetteth Faith; the meanes which doth confirm and keep men in the Covenant, is that which increaſeth and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eneth Faith; and the meanes which doth reclaim men from the breach of the Covenant, is that which doth chaſtiſe unbelief and diſobedience.</p>
               <p>5. To beget Faith, the ordinance of Preaching <hi>(h)</hi> is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed; <hi>(h)</hi> Rom. 10. 14. <hi>How ſhall they beleeve in him of whom they have not heard? and how ſhall they heare without a Preacher?</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 17. So then faith commeth by hearing, and hearing by the word of God.</hi>] To confirm it, <hi>(i)</hi> the ſame ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance is to be uſed, <hi>(i)</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 2. <hi>Deſire the ſincere milk of the word, that ye may grow thereby.</hi>] together with the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of <hi>(k)</hi> Prayer, <hi>(k)</hi> Act. 6. 4. <hi>But we will give our ſelves continually unto Prayer and to the miniſtry of the Word.</hi> and the right uſe of <hi>(l)</hi> Baptiſm; <hi>(l)</hi> Mat. 28. 19. <hi>Baptizing them in the name of the Father, &amp;c.</hi> &amp; Act. 2. 40. <hi>Then they that gladly received the word, were baptized.</hi>] and the <hi>(m)</hi> Lords ſupper; <hi>(m)</hi> Act. 2. 41. <hi>And they continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles doctrine, and fellowſhip and breaking of bread, and in prayer.</hi>] and the fellowſhip of the Saints by their <hi>(n)</hi> aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies; <hi>(n)</hi> Heb. 10. 25. <hi>Not forſaking the Aſſembling of our ſelves together,</hi> &amp;c.] and by the ſupporting of one another in their <hi>(o)</hi> burthens; <hi>(o)</hi> Gal. 6. 2. <hi>Beare ye one anothers bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, and ſo fulfill the law of Chriſt.</hi>] And to reclaim the diſobedient from the breach of the Covenant, the rod <hi>(p)</hi> of Diſcipline, <hi>(p)</hi> 1 Cor. 4. 21. <hi>Shall I come with a Rod,</hi> &amp;c. and weapons of <hi>(q)</hi> Revenge are appointed, <hi>(q)</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 6. <hi>Having in a readineſſe to Revenge all diſobedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. Theſe ordinances are not to be concealed, but by the publike profeſſion <hi>(r)</hi> of the Goſpel, adminiſtred in the Church. <hi>(r)</hi> Mat. 5. 14. <hi>Ye are the light of the world; a city that is ſet on a hill cannot be hid.</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 15. Neither do men light a candle and put it under a buſhell</hi>—v. 16. <hi>Let your light ſhine ſo before men, that they may ſee your good works, and glorifie your Father which is in heaven.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>7. The ordinances of Government are to be adminiſtred by thoſe, who are intruſted with the <hi>(s)</hi> Keyes of the kingdome of heaven, whoſe authority is to binde or looſe, and to remit or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:160191:20"/> retain ſinnes, according to the revealed will of God, mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterially, <hi>(s)</hi> Mat. 16. 19. <hi>And I will give thee the Keys of the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of heaven, and whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on earth ſhalbe bound in heaven; whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe on earth ſhall be looſed in heaven.</hi> &amp; Joh. 20. 23. <hi>Whoſoever ſinnes ye remit, they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted unto them; and whoſoever ſinnes ye retain, they are retained.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The key of Knowledge muſt alwayes make way for the key of Diſcipline; becauſe the weapons of Righteouſneſſe muſt firſt lead the minds of men captive, and convict their conſciences <hi>(t)</hi> before they be made uſe of to revenge diſobedience. <hi>(t)</hi> 2 Cor. 10. 4, 5. <hi>The weapons of our warfare are mighty through God to the pulling down of ſtrong holds; caſting down imaginations, and every high thing that exalteth it ſelf againſt the knowledge of God;</hi> and <hi>bringing into captivity every thought unto the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Chriſt;</hi> and <hi>having in a readineſſe to revenge all diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, when your obedience is fulfilled,</hi> &amp; Luk. 11. 52. <hi>Ye have taken away the key of knowledge,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Concerning the office &amp; imployment of the Paſtor and Teacher.</head>
               <p>1. THat Chriſt Jeſus hath appointed Paſtors and Teachers to be officers in his Church, is evident from <hi>Joh. 10. 1, 2. the Sheep-fold—the Shepherd of the ſheep.</hi> Epheſ. 4. 11. <hi>He gave—ſome Paſtors and Teachers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. That to theſe officers, the whole work and effect of the ordinary Adminiſtration is committed, is alſo evident from <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4, 11, till 17. where next unto the extraordinary officers of the church, who are Apoſtles, Prophets and Evangeliſts; the ordinary, who are Paſtors and Teachers, are ranked: unto whom, together with the others, all is aſcribed, that is to be done concerning the Church. Therefore the extraordinary offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ceaſing, all is committed unto the ordinary adminiſtration, which reſteth upon theſe, 1 <hi>Pet. 5. 1, 2, 3, 4. Feed the flock,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) ſhepherdize the flock.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:160191:21"/>
               <p>3. That theſe officers are diſtinct from Ruling Elders; and that Ruling Elders are ſubordinate unto their imployment, is cleer from 1 <hi>Tim. 5. 17. The Elders that Rule well—eſpecially they that labour in the word and doctrine.</hi> That they are alſo di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from Deacons, and that theſe are ſubordinate unto them in like manner, is cleer from <hi>Act. 6. 2, 3, 4. It is not reaſon we ſhould leave the Word, and ſerve tables—Look out men—whom we may appoint over this buſines; but we will give our ſelves to Prayer and to the miniſtery of the Word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. That in the work of the Miniſtery, the duties of the Paſtor and Teacher are to be jointly performed, doth appeare by this; that <hi>the Paſtors according to Gods heart, do feed the people with knowledge and underſtanding,</hi> Jer. 3. 15. Then alſo <hi>reproofs, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes, and exhortations,</hi> which are the proper work of the Paſtor, muſt be performed; <hi>with all long ſuffering and doctrine:</hi> which is the proper work of the Teacher, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 2.</p>
               <p>5. That the ſpeciall gifts and proper works of both theſe, are nevertheleſſe diſtinct; is alſo apparent from <hi>Rom. 12. 6, 7, 8. Having gifts differing—He that teacheth, on teaching; He that exhorteth, on exhortation.</hi> And 1 <hi>Cor. 12. 8. To one is given—the word of wiſdome,</hi> which is the Paſtoral; <hi>to another the word of knowledge,</hi> which is the Doctoral gift.</p>
               <p>6. So then the Paſtoral office doth eminently contain the uſe of all other offices: for all that is to be done by the Teacher, or by the Ruling Elder, or the Deacon, is to be ſubſervient unto this care; and in caſe theſe officers be wanting, the Paſtor is to do all by himſelf, even as the Apoſtles did the work of the Deacons before thoſe officers were choſen, <hi>Act. 4. 34, 35. They laid down the prices at the Apoſtles feet, and diſtribution was made.</hi> And when all theſe do their duties, he ought carefully to concurre with them therein, <hi>Rom. 12. 5. We being many are one body; and every one members one of another.</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 20. <hi>They are many members, yet but one body.</hi> verſ. 25. <hi>The members ſhould have the ſame care one of another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>7. The end and uſe of the Paſtoral office, is the ſame with the end and uſe of the Apoſtolical, Prophetical, and Evangelical office. Which is, <hi>to perfect the Saints; to do the work of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery; and to build up the body of Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 12.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:160191:21"/>
               <p>8. The effect of this office, when it is rightly performed, will be,</p>
               <p>1. <hi>The unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the ſon of God, unto a perfect man,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 13.</p>
               <p>2. Preſervation from (<hi>a</hi>) ſeducers. (<hi>a</hi>) Epheſ. 4. 14. <hi>That we henceforth be no more children, toſſed to and fro and carried about with every winde of doctrine, by the ſlight of men and cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning craftineſſe whereby they lie in wait to deceive.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>3. The growth (<hi>b</hi>) of the Body in all things in Chriſt. (<hi>b</hi>) Epheſ. 4. 15. <hi>But ſpeaking the truth in love, in all things, may grow up unto him which is the head, even Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. The jointing (<hi>c</hi>) and compacting of the Body together under Chriſt; that the Members may act within themſelves for the building up of each other in love. (<hi>c</hi>) Epheſ. 4. 16. <hi>The whole Body fitly joyned together and compacted by that which every joint ſupplieth, according to the effectuall working in the meaſure of every part, maketh increaſe of the Body to the edifying of it ſelf in love.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>9. To gain theſe ends and effects, three things are requiſite in the Paſtor.</p>
               <p>Firſt, that his entry upon the office be lawfull.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that the duties proper to it be diſcharged.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, that the ſpirituall manner of performing thoſe duties be obſerved.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>1. <hi>Of the Entry upon the office.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>10. The lawfull entry upon the Paſtorall charge, is onely to come in by the <hi>door;</hi> and he that doth enter into the ſheepfold <hi>any other way, is a thief and a robber,</hi> Joh. 10. 1, 2.</p>
                  <p>11. The door by which the ſhepherd muſt come, is Chriſt, Joh. 10. 9. <hi>I am the door; by me if any man enter, he ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>12. Now Chriſt by the annointing of the Spirit doth dwell in the (<hi>d</hi>) hearts of the faithfull, (<hi>d</hi>) 2 Cor. 1. 21, 22. <hi>Now he which ſtabliſheth us with you in Chriſt, and hath annointed us is God; who hath alſo ſealed us, and given the earneſt of his ſpirit in our hearts.</hi> &amp; 2 Cor. 3. 17. <hi>Now the Lord is the Spirit.</hi> &amp; Epheſ. 3. 16, 17. <hi>Grant you—to be ſtrengthened with might
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:160191:22"/> by his Spirit in the inner man; that Chriſt may dwell in your hearts by faith.</hi>] If then a Miniſter doth offer himſelf by the Spirit with that Paſtoral affection which proceedeth from Chriſt unto the flock; He who is both the (<hi>e</hi>) Door, and the (<hi>f</hi>) Porter, doth open himſelf in the heart of the Flock to receive him, and he enters in lawfully. (<hi>e</hi>) Joh. 10. 9. <hi>I am the door,</hi> &amp;c. compared with <hi>verſe 3. To him</hi> (viz. that entreth by the door) <hi>the Porter openeth.</hi> And with <hi>Revel. 3. 7. He that hath the key of David, that openeth and no man ſhutteth, and ſhutteth and no man openeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>13. If any man hath not this Paſtorall affection and ſpirit which Chriſt had towards the flock; but commeth in <hi>ſome other way,</hi> that is, by ſome humane practiſes and contrivances of his own; Chriſt doth call him a <hi>thief and a robber,</hi> Joh. 10. 1. and ſaith, that he doth come <hi>to ſteal, to kill, and to deſtroy,</hi> ibid. v. 10. The heart then of the Flock muſt be opened to him that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth unto them, elſe he cannot pretend to be the Paſtor of their ſoules.</p>
                  <p>14. This door of the heart being firſt opened by the inward working of Chriſts ſpirit; the outward call alſo muſt follow upon, by a free choiſe, and orderly reception of him that is choſen, in a publike way, in the face of the Congregation, with the countenance of Authority; as <hi>Aaron</hi> was called &amp; received, Hebr. 5. 4. <hi>No man taketh this honour to himſelf, but he that is called of God as Aaron was.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>II. <hi>Of the Duties belonging to the office.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>15. The duties belonging to the Paſtorall charge contain all the cares and endeavours, whereby the Flock is to be fed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted, preſerved and defended.</p>
                  <p>16. The cares belonging to the feeding of the flock, are theſe—</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to ſeek and find out paſture for them, <hi>Joh. 10. 9. By me if any man enter in, he ſhall—find paſture.</hi> Which is done, by <hi>giving attendance to reading,</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 13. by meditating and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying himſelf to profit in knowledge, 1 Tim. 4. 15. <hi>Meditate upon theſe things, give thy ſelf wholly to them, that thy profiting may appeare to all.</hi> And to this effect he muſt keep the form of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:160191:22"/> Doctrine received from the Apoſtles, and the Truth of grace received from the Holy Ghoſt, both which are recommended to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 1. 13, 14. <hi>Hold faſt the forme of ſonnd words which thou haſt heard of me, in faith and love, which is in Chriſt Jeſus. Keep by the Holy Ghoſt which dwelleth in us, that good thing which was committed unto thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, to give to the Flock that paſture which he find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be their proper portion. <hi>Luke 12. 42. Give them their portion of meat;</hi> which is done by dividing the Word to them, 2 <hi>Tim. 2. 15. Study to ſhew thy ſelf approved unto God, a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man that needeth not be aſhamed; rightly dividing the word of truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to give this portion in due ſeaſon. <hi>Luke 12. 42. Give them in due ſeaſon their portion of meat.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, to give it according to every mans capacitie. <hi>Mark 4 33. He ſpake the word unto them as they were able to heare it.</hi> Then he muſt <hi>give to babes, milk;</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 2. and to thoſe that are of <hi>full age, ſtrong meat,</hi> Heb. 5. 12, 13, 14. He muſt <hi>feed all with judgement,</hi> Ezech. 34. 16. He muſt not <hi>feed the weak with doubtfull diſputations,</hi> Rom. 14. 1. Nor entertain with any, <hi>profane and vain bablings, and oppoſitions of a Science falſly ſo called,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 20. &amp; 2 Tim. 2. 16. <hi>Or queſtions and ſtrife of words,</hi> 1 Tim. 6. 4. and <hi>contentions</hi> of <hi>Genealogies,</hi> Tit. 3. 9.</p>
                  <p>17. The food to be given to the flock, is the word of God, Mat. 4. 4. <hi>Man liveth not by bread alone, but by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of God.</hi> This word of God, is none other but the faithfull word which the Apoſtles taught, <hi>Tit. 1. 9. Holding faſt the faithfull word as he hath been taught.</hi> And all the word is taught, to the end that <hi>it may beget Charity out of a pure heart, and of a good Conſcience, and of Faith unfained.</hi> 1 Tim. 1. 5.</p>
                  <p>18. The cares belonging to the conduct of the Flock, are theſe—</p>
                  <p>Firſt, the good Shepherd ought to <hi>call his ſheep by name,</hi> Joh. 10, 3.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, he ought <hi>to lead them out and in,</hi> Joh. 10. 3, 9.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to <hi>go before them,</hi> Joh. 10. 4. to <hi>be an example of the believers, in word, in converſation, in charity, &amp;c.</hi> 1 Tim. 4. 12.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:160191:23"/>
                  <p>Fourthly, <hi>To viſit the flock,</hi> and <hi>ſeek out the young ones,</hi> Zach. 1. 16. and <hi>judge between cattell and cattell,</hi> Ezek. 34. 17.</p>
                  <p>19. The cares belonging to the preſervation and defence of the Flock, are theſe—</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to pray conſtantly for the flock, as the Apoſtle doth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 9. &amp; 1. <hi>Cor. 1. 4. Epheſ. 1. 16. Phil. 1. 3, 4. Col. 1. 3, 4, 9.</hi> &amp; 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1. 2, 3.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to warne them of dangers, as the Apoſtle did the Epheſians, <hi>Act.</hi> 20. 31. and God doth charge watchmen to do, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 3, 17. &amp; 33, 3.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to be helpfull to them in all their infirmities, that is, <hi>to beare the ſheep that ſtandeth ſtill,</hi> Zach. 11. 16. <hi>to heale and ſtrengthen the ſick and bind up the broken,</hi> Ezek. 34. 4. <hi>to comfort the feeble and ſupport the weake,</hi> 1 Theſſ. 5. 14. <hi>to reſtore thoſe that are tak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n in a fault,</hi> Gal. 6. 1.</p>
                  <p>4. <hi>To bring back that which is driven away, and ſeek out that which is loſt,</hi> Ezek. 34. 4.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, to reſiſt the <hi>ravenous wolves,</hi> and <hi>men ſpeaking perverſe things,</hi> Act. 20. 29, 30. <hi>to convince gainſayers, and ſtop the mouths of unruly and vain talkers,</hi> Tit. 1. 9, 10, 11. <hi>To reject hereticks,</hi> Tit. 2. 10.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, to <hi>lay down his life for the ſheep,</hi> to defend them, and <hi>not as a hireling to run away from them,</hi> Joh. 10. 10, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>And thus much of the Duties: now followeth to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>III. <hi>The ſpirituall way, how theſe Duties ſhould be performed.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>20. The manner and way of performing theſe Duties, is not arbitrary, depending upon the wit, or will and contrivance of mans wiſdome; but ſpiritually to be regulated either by the Word which is expreſſed, or by the undoubted Principles of Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication. 1 <hi>Cor. 2. 1. I came not with excellency of ſpeech or of wiſdome.</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 4. My ſpeech was not with enticing words of mans wiſdome, but in demonſtration of the Spirit, and of power.</hi> &amp; 2 <hi>Cor. 1. 12. Not with worldly wiſdome, but by the grace of God we have had our converſation in the world, and more abundantly to you<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:160191:23"/> &amp; chap. 4. 12. <hi>Not walking in craftineſſe, or handling the word of God deceitfully.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>21. The way then to regulate and order theſe Duties, hath three Spirituall paths:</p>
                  <p>The firſt is, that which ſetteth the Paſtors ſpirit upon his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per imployment.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond, that whereby his endeavours are fitted towards the Flock, and the Flock fitted to receive them at his hand.</p>
                  <p>The third is, that wherein his imployment is made edifying and uſefull towards all. In the firſt path, he will be accepted of God; in the ſecond and third, approved of men.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the firſt Path.</head>
                  <p>22. The Paſtors ſpirit will be directed towards the work of his imployment, if he beare in minde,</p>
                  <p>What his relation is to God, in his office.</p>
                  <p>What the end and uſe of his work is.</p>
                  <p>And what the frame of his Affections, and Rules of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance ſhould be, to make his way anſwerable unto theſe.</p>
                  <p>23. His relation unto God, is, that God doth intruſt him with his Myſteries, and with the ſoules of his children: As a ſteward to diſpenſe the myſteries unto Gods children; to have inſpection over them, and to keep the Keyes of the Houſe of GOD.</p>
                  <p>24. As a ſteward thus intruſted: the frame of his Affection muſt be <hi>Faithfulneſſe (a</hi>) towards his Maſter; and the rule of his Performance muſt be, to ſtudy <hi>to approve his conſcience</hi> to God, not regarding the judgement of men, but that of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone. (<hi>a</hi>) 1 Cor. 4. 1. <hi>Let a man ſo account of us as of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of Chriſt, and Stewards of the myſteries of God.</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 2. It is required in ſtewards, that a man be found Faithfull.</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 3. With mrit is a ſmall thing that I ſhould be judged by you, or of mans judgement. v. 4. I know nothing by my ſelf, yet am I not hereby juſtified; but he that juſtifieth me is the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>25. The myſteries wherewith he is intruſted, are the Word and the Ordinances.</p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:160191:24"/>
                  <p>26. As a Steward intruſted with the Word; the frame of his Affection muſt be <hi>Sincerity, (b</hi>) not to mixe any ſelf-ends with the Word. (<hi>b</hi>) 2 Cor. 2. 17. <hi>We corrupt not the Word; but as of ſincerity, as of God, in the ſight of God, ſpeak we in Chriſt.</hi>] And the rule of Performance in reference to God, is to ſpeak as in his ſight and preſence: and in reference to men, to renounce the hidden (<hi>c</hi>) things of diſhoneſty, and by the manifeſtation of the truth, to approve himſelf to the conſcience of every one. (<hi>c</hi>) 2 Cor. 4. 2. <hi>We have renounced the hidden things of diſhoneſty,—but by the manifeſtation of the Truth commending our ſelves to every mans conſcience in the ſight of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>27. Then alſo, as a ſteward intruſted with the Ordinances; the frame of his ſpirit and affections muſt be free from prejudice, not preferring one Ordinance before another: And the rules of Performance are, to diſpence the Ordinances (<hi>d</hi>) impartially, (<hi>d</hi>) 1 Tim. 5. 21. <hi>I charge thee—that thou obſerve theſe things without preferring one before another, doing nothing by partiality.</hi>] and to keep himſelf and the holy things pure: Himſelf, by not (<hi>e</hi>) partaking of other mens ſinnes; (<hi>e</hi>) 1 Tim. 5. 22. <hi>Neither be partaker of other mens ſinnes; keep thy ſelf pure.</hi>] the Holy things, by not giving them unto dogs (<hi>f</hi>) and ſwine; (<hi>f</hi>) Mat. 7. 6. <hi>Give not that which is holy unto the dogs, neither caſt ye your pearls before ſwine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>28. To diſcharge the truth committed unto him concerning the ſoules of Gods children; the frame of his Affections muſt be Faithfulneſſe unto them, for Gods ſake; and watchfulneſſe over them, as one that muſt (<hi>g</hi>) give an account, (<hi>g</hi>) Heb. 13. 17. <hi>They watch for your ſoules, as they that muſt give an account.</hi>] And accordingly the rule of his Performance unto them, muſt be, in diſpenſing the Word, to with-hold nothing from them which is profitable touching the whole (<hi>h</hi>) counſel of God, (<hi>h</hi>) Act. 20. 20. <hi>I have kept back nothing that was profitable unto you.</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 27. I have not ſhunned to declare unto you all the counſel of God.</hi>] And in diſpenſing the Ordinances, to be <hi>jealous over them with a godly jealouſie, leſt they ſhould be corrupted from the ſimplicity which is in Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 2, 3.</p>
                  <p>29. The end and uſe of the work is, that Gods glory through Jeſus Chriſt; and the common edification (<hi>i</hi>) of every one by
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:160191:24"/> another, through the right uſe of Gods graces, may be advanced. (<hi>i</hi>) 1 Pet. 4. 10, 11. <hi>As every man hath received the gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another—that God in all things may be glorified through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>30. And the frame of the Affection whereby the ſpirit of the Paſtor will be enabled to reach this end, is (<hi>k</hi>) Love. (<hi>k</hi>) 1 Cor. 8. 1. <hi>Charity edifyeth.</hi> &amp; 1 Cor. 13. 1, 2, 3. <hi>Though I ſpeak with the tongue of men and angels; and have no charity, I am as ſounding braſſe and a tinkling cymball: And though I have the gift of Prophecie, and underſtand all myſteries and all knowledge, and though I have all faith ſo that I could remove mountains, and have no charity, I am nothing: And though I beſtow all my goods to feed the poor, and though I give my body to be burnt, and have no charity, it profiteth me nothing.</hi> &amp; Epheſ. 4. 15. <hi>Speaking the truth in love, ye may grow up unto him in all things.</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 16. the Body unto the edifying of it ſelf in love.</hi>] And the Rule of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance ſubſervient hereunto, for matter of Doctrine, is, to <hi>ſpeak as the oracles of God:</hi> and for matter of Action, is, to <hi>doe as of the ability which God doth give,</hi> 1 Pet. 4. 11.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The ſecond Path.</head>
                  <p>31. The way to fit all Paſtorall endeavours to the Flock, is threefold:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to make the work of the Miniſtery free from all world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly aimes; as, to (<hi>l</hi>) pleaſe men, to get (<hi>m</hi>) profit, or to get (<hi>n</hi>) humane glory. (<hi>l</hi>) 1 Theſſ. 2. 4. <hi>We ſpeak not as pleaſing men, but God which tryeth our hearts; for neither at any time uſed we flattering words. (m</hi>) Ibid. v. 5. <hi>Nor uſed we a cloak of covetouſneſſe. (n</hi>) Ibid. v. 6. <hi>Nor of men ſought we glory, neither of you nor of others.</hi>] to be free from entanglements of (<hi>o</hi>) worldly cares, <hi>o</hi>) 2 Tim. 2, 3, 4. <hi>Endure hardneſſe as a good ſouldier of Jeſus Chriſt: no man that warreth entangleth himſelf with the affairs of this life; that he may pleaſe him who hath choſen him to be a ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier.</hi>] And not to be engaged to adminiſter worldly (<hi>p</hi>) judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catures in order to the civil Magiſtrate, (<hi>p</hi>) Luk. 12. 13, 14. <hi>And one of the company ſaid unto him</hi> (viz. to Chriſt) <hi>Maſter, ſpeak to my brother, that he divide the inheritance with me: And he
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:160191:25"/> ſaid unto him, Man, who made me a Judge or a divider a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, to do the work towards the Flock, with a willing (<hi>q</hi>) and ready minde without conſtraint, (<hi>q</hi>) 1 Pet. 5. 2. <hi>Feed the flock—taking the care thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly, not for filthy lucre, but of a ready minde.</hi>] with all gentleneſſe and tenderneſſe of affection, and nurſe-like (<hi>r</hi>) loving care, (<hi>r</hi>) 1 Theſſ. 2. 7, 8. <hi>But we were gentle among you, even as a nurſe cheriſheth her children: So being affectionately deſirous of you, we were willing to have imparted unto you, not the Goſpel of God only, but alſo our own ſoules, becauſe you were deare to us.</hi>] With all juſt, holy, and unblameable (<hi>s</hi>) outward behaviour, (<hi>s</hi>) 1 Theſſ. 2. 10. <hi>You are witneſſes, and God alſo, how holily, juſtly, and unblameably we have behaved our ſelves among you that believe.</hi>] And without all burdens (<hi>t</hi>) unto the Flock, ſo far as can be poſſibly. (<hi>t</hi>) 1 Theſſ. 2. 6, 9. <hi>We might have been bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome as the Apoſtles of Chriſt—But ye remember our labour and travell, for labouring night and day, becauſe we would not be chargeable unto any.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to undergoe any inconvenience whatſoever, rather then to give occaſion (<hi>u</hi>) of offence unto any at the Goſpel, (<hi>u</hi>) 2 Cor. 6. 3, 4. <hi>Giving no offence in any thing, that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery be not blamed; but in all things approving our ſelves as the Miniſters of God, in much patience, in afflictions, in neceſſities, in diſtreſſes,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>32. The way to fit the Flock to receive and admit of all Paſtorall duties at their Paſtors hands, is fourfold:</p>
                  <p>Firſt, to walk openly (<hi>x</hi>) and in the light towards them, (<hi>x</hi>) Joh. 3. 21. <hi>He that doth the truth commeth to the light, that his deeds may be made manifeſt, that they are wrought in God.</hi> &amp; 1 Joh. 1. 7. <hi>If we walk in the light, as he is in the light, we have fellowſhip one with another.</hi> Now God is in the light, by the manifeſtation of his truth to the conſcience; if therefore a Paſtor doth walk in this light to the Flock, he will fit them to receive his adminiſtration.] Which ought to be done by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring and pre-informing their underſtandings concerning the courſe which is to be taken towards them; that they may not ſeem to be ſurpriſed, or bound to walk by an implicite faith
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:160191:25"/> under their Paſtor, in blind ſubmiſſion.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, to make them ſenſible that all is done miniſterially, as a ſervice of love unto them, and to be a <hi>help unto their joy,</hi> and not to exerciſe any <hi>dominion over their Faith,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 24. or (<hi>y) Lord it</hi> over their perſons, (<hi>y</hi>) 1 Pet. 5. 3. <hi>Neither as being Lords over Gods heritage, but being enſamples to the flock.</hi>] And yet not to give them occaſion to take authority over their Paſtor, or to (<hi>a</hi>) deſpiſe him, (<hi>a</hi>) 1 Tim. 4. 12. <hi>Let no man deſpiſe thy youth.</hi> &amp; Tit. 2. 15. <hi>Exhort and rebuke with all authority; let no man deſpiſe thee.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, to deale with every one of them as well in (<hi>b</hi>) private <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in publike, as need may be, (<hi>b</hi>) Act. 20. 20. <hi>I kept back no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that was profitable unto you, but have ſhewed you and have taught you publikely, and from houſe to houſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, to bring them to a contract with Chriſt, as eſpouſed, (<hi>c</hi>) and to be preſented unto him, (<hi>c</hi>) 2 Cor. 11. 2. <hi>I have eſpouſed you unto one husband, that I may preſent you as a chaste Virgin unto Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>The third Path.</head>
                  <p>33. Although every Paſtor is authoriſed in himſelf, by his office, to lead and rule the Flock; and as one who is accountable unto God, muſt diſcharge his conſcience in the obſervation and practice of all Gods ordinances; And that every Congregation hath full power to do all things for its own edification, <hi>decently and by an order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. 40. Yet by the Rules of holy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion (<hi>d</hi>) in Chriſtianity, no Paſtor, nor Flock, nor Chriſtian alſo ought to walk or ſtand by himſelf alone, if poſſibly they can be joyned unto others in the publike profeſſion (<hi>d</hi>) Epheſ. 4. 1. <hi>Walk worthy of the vocation wherewith you are called.</hi> &amp; <hi>v. 3. Endeavouring to keep the unity of the ſpirit in the bond of peace.</hi> v. 4, 5. <hi>One body, one ſpirit, even as ye are called in one hope of your calling; one Lord, one faith, one baptiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> v. 6. <hi>one God and Father.</hi> &amp; v. 14. <hi>Till we all come to the unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the Sonne of God, unto a perfect man.</hi> &amp; v. 14. <hi>That we be no more toſſed to and fro, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>rried about with every wind of doctrine.</hi> v. 16. <hi>The whole body fitly joyned
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:160191:26"/> together and compacted.</hi> &amp; 1 Cor. 9. 19. <hi>Though I am free from all men, yet I made my ſelf a ſervant unto all, that I might gain the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> v. 20. <hi>To the Jewes I became as a Jew—to them that are under the Law, as under the Law.</hi>—v. 21. <hi>To them that are without Law, as without Law, (being not without law to God, but under the law to Chriſt) that I might gain them that are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out law.</hi> v. 22. <hi>To the weak I became as weak—I am made all things to all—And this I do for the Goſpels ſake, that I might be made partaker thereof with you.</hi>] If the Apoſtle did thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcend to all, to be partaker of the Goſpel with thoſe that had an intereſt in it; then, all that have any intereſt in the Goſpel, ought to condeſcend one to another, to partake of the ſame each with other; and conſequently, no man ought to ſtand alone in the profeſſion.</p>
                  <p>34. So then, every Miniſter of the Goſpel, in the duties of his Miniſterial charge, is bound in conſcience to maintain a Brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly communion and correſpondency with his neighbour Miniſters; chiefly in matters of common and publike concernment. So that every one is bound to ask the queſtion which the Spouſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth unto Chriſt in the <hi>Canticles,</hi> chap. 1. 7. <hi>Tell me (O thou whom my ſoule loveth) where thou feedeſt, where thou makeſt thy flock to reſt at noon?</hi> And then to follow the duty preſcribed in (<hi>e</hi>) the Anſwer, (<hi>e</hi>) Cant. 1. 8. <hi>Go thy way forth by the footſteps of the flock, and feed thy kids beſides the ſhepherds tents.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>35. By which means all the Congregations of Profeſſours will be, as they ought to be, co-ordinate unto each other, as <hi>companies of horſes in Pharaohs chariots,</hi> Cant. 1. 9. combined in the ſame warfare for the ſame Kings ſervice.</p>
                  <p>36. Now this conjunction and co-ordination of Churches, by the brotherly combination of their Leaders; as it may not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judge the liberty which they have in Chriſt, ſo it ſhould oblige them to a right uſe of that liberty, to make it ſerviceable unto each other in the communion of Saints.</p>
                  <p>37. It cannot be ſerviceable to this end, and binding, without a free, willing, mutuall agreement of Brethren to walk in the ſame publike wayes; Firſt, of Doctrine and of Worſhip, for the honour of God; ſecondly, of Government, for the good of Believers, to ſtrengthen them in the way of the Heavenly calling;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:160191:26"/> Thirdly, of Diſcipline, for the rooting out of vice and ſcandals which diſhonour the profeſſion.</p>
                  <p>38. To make this agreement free and mutuall, there muſt be ſome Aſſemblies and Conferences ſetled; and theſe ſo ordered, that all things ſhall be carried with that equality, that none ſhall have cauſe to think himſelf borne down or excluded from his right, or paſt by and concluded without his conſent in matters which do concern him.</p>
                  <p>39. And to do this, two things muſt needs be determined: Firſt, what the orderly conſtitution of the Aſſemblies muſt be, in their Members, and method of handling matters by way of conference: Secondly, what the matters are which they ſhould meddle withall; and what the things are which they ſhould not meddle withall.</p>
                  <p>40. In all which, beſides that which is cleerly to be gathered from the word of God, the practiſes and the tryed courſes of the Reformed churches ſhould be taken into conſideration, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentially applied unto the circumſtances of our preſent condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherein I beſeech God to direct us to his glory, in the advancement of our peace. Amen.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> Concerning the office and imployment of Ruling Elders.</head>
               <p>THat Ruling (<hi>a</hi>) Elders are officers in the Church of God, may be cleerly gathered from <hi>Rom. 12. 8. He that ruleth with diligence. (a</hi>) 1 Tim. 5. 17. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well be counted worthy of double-honour, chiefly thoſe that labour in the word and doctrine.</hi> &amp; 1 Cor. 12. 28. <hi>God hath ſet in the Church—Governments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. That they are officers diſtinct from other officers, is alſo plain from the ſame place; chiefly from that of 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. and from <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 4, 6. compared with 8. For in 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. 17. he doth mention two ſorts of Elders: firſt in the generall thoſe that rule well; ſecondly more diſtinctly, thoſe that in bearing rule, labour in the word and doctrine. And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 4. the Apoſtle ſaith, that there are many members in the body of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:160191:27"/> Church, and that they have not all of them the ſame offices: then, <hi>v.</hi> 6. he ſaith, that the gifts of grace which makes men ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of offices, are different: and then in the latter part of <hi>v.</hi> 6. and <hi>v.</hi> 7. &amp; 8. he ſheweth what the particular differences of offices are, amongſt which he reckoneth up that of Ruling; from whence it followeth, that the Ruler is not only an officer, but a different officer from the others named in that place.</p>
               <p>3. The nature of the office belonging to them may be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, 1. By the names given to it; 2. By the things about which it is converſant; 3. By the end which it hath in being converſant thereabout; 4. By the parts of the work to be done in it.</p>
               <p>Firſt, the Names given to theſe Elders are, Rulers, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Overſeers, Stewards.</p>
               <p>The name of <hi>Ruler</hi> in the originall is twofold; one doth import Superiority, another Action; the firſt is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; both are tranſlated Rulers: but <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſignifie one that ſtandeth over others in authority; and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> doth properly ſignifie one that doth lead and guide o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the way wherein they ought to walk.</p>
               <p>The name of <hi>Governour,</hi> doth ſignifie one that giveth directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and addreſſes whereby others are ordered in a courſe, as a ſhip by him that ſitteth at the helm thereof.</p>
               <p>The name of <hi>Overſeer</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) doth import both authority and action, by the inſpection which a Superior doth take of one that is under his charge.</p>
               <p>The name of <hi>Steward,</hi> doth ſignifie one that is to ſee the laws and orders of his Maſters houſe obſerved; and hath the keyes thereof committed unto his keeping.</p>
               <p>2. The Things about which the charge is converſant, are (in generall) the Church, and ſuch as may be gained thereunto. Which is the ſpirituall (<hi>b</hi>) houſe and tabernacle of God, (<hi>b</hi>) Epheſ. 2. 21, 22. <hi>It</hi> (viz. the building) <hi>groweth unto an holy temple in the Lord—an habitation of God through the Spirit.</hi>] the body (<hi>c</hi>) of Chriſt, (<hi>q</hi>) 1 Cor. 12. 27. <hi>Now ye are the body of Chriſt, and members in particular.</hi>] and the Kingdome which is not of this (<hi>d</hi>) world; (<hi>d</hi>) Joh. 18. 36. <hi>My kingdome is not of this world.</hi>] and therefore is not to be governed by the lawes of this world, nor can the officers thereof claim their calling and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:160191:27"/> authority from this world, nor ought they to meddle in their charge with the (<hi>e</hi>) affairs of this world, (<hi>e</hi>) Luk. 12. 14. <hi>Who made me a Judge, or a divider over you?</hi> If Chriſt was no Judge or divider in worldly matters; then none of his Officers, as under him.</p>
               <p>In particular; this office is converſant about the Religious profeſſion and life of thoſe that belong in any reſpect to the Church, whether they be in, or out of office.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, the End wherefore the Elders are converſant about theſe things, is, that they ſhould look both to the Church and to the Members thereof: to edifie that, and preſerve it from ſcandals; and to make theſe fit to walk worthy of the calling by which they are called in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>4. The parts of their work are the ſeverall duties whereunto they are obliged, which are chiefly theſe—</p>
               <p>Firſt, in reſpect of God, they are his (<hi>f</hi>) ſtewards, (<hi>f</hi>) Tit. 1. v. 5. with 7. <hi>Thou ſhouldeſt ordain Elders in every city, as I appointed thee; if any be blameleſſe—for a Biſhop</hi> (an Overſeer) <hi>muſt be blameleſſe as the ſteward of God.</hi>] and therefore muſt be (<hi>g</hi>) faithfull, (<hi>g</hi>) 1 Cor. 4. 2. <hi>It is required in Stewards, that a man be found faithfull,</hi>] and adminiſter their charge ſo, as to be (<hi>h</hi>) accountable unto him, (<hi>h</hi>) Heb. 13. 17. <hi>Watch for your ſoules, as they that muſt give an account.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, in reſpect of the Church; they muſt take (<hi>i</hi>) care of it, (<hi>i</hi>) 1 Tim. 3. 5. <hi>If a man know not how to rule his own houſe, how ſhall he take care of the Church of God?</hi>] and that with (<hi>k</hi>) diligence, (<hi>k</hi>) Rom. 12. 8. <hi>He that ruleth, with diligence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, in reſpect of the Members thereof, they muſt (<hi>l</hi>) watch over them, (<hi>l</hi>) Heb. 13. 17. <hi>They watch over your ſoules</hi>] take pains for them, and (<hi>m</hi>) admoniſh them as occaſion ſhall require, (<hi>m</hi>) 1 Theſſ. 5. 12. <hi>Which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, in reſpect of the End of their imployment, they muſt be intereſſed and ingaged,</p>
               <p n="1">1. In the election, calling, and dimiſſion of Officers to and from charges in the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the admiſſion of worthy, and rejection of unworthy Members.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:160191:28"/>3. In the ordering of all matters of publike worſhip, to be dutifully and decently performed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the moderating of the carriage of matters at publike meetings, whereunto the Body of the Congregation is to be invited.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In the redreſſing of Scandals, by way of inſtruction, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, admonition, or cenſure, if need be.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In the reſtoring of the penitent, in healing of breaches, in the preſerving of all in the unity of the Spirit, in the helping of the weak to beare their burdens, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging of every one in the wayes of truth and righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In the viſiting of the (<hi>n</hi>) ſick, eſpecially when they are ſent for; to give them comfort, and pray for them, (<hi>n</hi>) Jam. 5. 14. <hi>Is any man ſick, let him call the Elders of the Church, and let them pray over him, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. The manner how this office ſhould be executed, is, That together with the Paſtor, in all matters of Spirituall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, as well in the Conſiſtoriall, as in the Claſſicall and Synodicall meetings, to give adviſe, and according to the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions to act by common conſent: and as the Paſtor ought not to act by himſelf, without their knowledge, any things of common concernment; ſo much leſſe ought they to act with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his approbation, and the conſent of each other, or at leaſt of the major part of the Elderſhip, upon mature delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:160191:28"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Some Rules taken from the Word of GOD, to ſhew, How the Elderſhips of a particular Church ought to ſettle the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Government of the Flock committed to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. THe end and uſe of all Church-Offices and Government, is this; <hi>Fitly to compact the members of Chriſts body to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by that which every joynt ſupplieth; that it may grow up in Chriſt in all things, and edifie it ſelf in love.</hi> Epheſ. 4. 15, 16.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To bring this to paſſe, as every one ought to <hi>walk worthy of the vocation wherewith he is called, in the unity of the Spirit with his Brethren,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. So more eſpecially ought the Officers of the Church thus to walke before others, <hi>thinking ſoberly of themſelves, according as God hath dealt unto them the meaſure of Faith,</hi> and gift of Adminiſtration. <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 3, 4, 5.</p>
               <p n="3">3. But if <hi>two cannot walk together except they be agreed,</hi> as the Prophet ſaith, <hi>Amos</hi> 3. 3. far leſſe can many do ſo, except they be agreed: therefore in all undertakings an agreement is to be ſought for. Firſt amongſt the Members of the Elderſhip within themſelves; Secondly, between the Elderſhip and the Flock over which they are ſet; Thirdly, between one Church and its Neighbour-churches, if theſe at all be concerned in the matter; And laſtly, between the Churches that are united and concerned in each other, and the Civil Magiſtrate, if the thing wherein they are agreed hath any reference unto the publique. And this Rule of proceeding is grounded upon theſe precepts: <hi>If it be poſſible, as much as lieth in you, live peaceably with all men,</hi> Rom. 12. 18. <hi>And give none offence neither to the Jewes nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. 32. <hi>Let every one of us pleaſe his Neighbour, to his edification for good</hi> Rom. 15. 2. Phil. 2. 4.</p>
               <p n="4">4. To gain theſe Agreements, three things muſt be found and made apparent in every ſpirituall work of Government:
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:160191:29"/> One, in the Matter; another, in the End thereof; and a third, in the Manner of performing it.</p>
               <p>Firſt in the Matter, it muſt appeare, that the thing to be done is in it ſelf lawfull, that is, agreeable to the will and purpoſe of Chriſt, and no wayes prejudiciall to any of his lawes who is the onely (<hi>a</hi>) Lawgiver of the Church, (<hi>a</hi>) Jam. 4. 12. <hi>There is one Law-giver; who is able to ſave and to deſtroy,</hi> Mat. 17. 5. <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed; heare ye him.</hi> &amp; Iſa. 33. 22. <hi>The Lord is our Judge, the Lord is our law-giver, the Lord is our King; he will ſave us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly in the End, it muſt appeare, that the undertaking of the work is intended only as a duty towards God, and a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of love (<hi>b</hi>) towards the Saints; (<hi>b</hi>) Gal. 5. 13. <hi>By love ſerve one another.</hi> &amp; 1 Pet. 4. 10, 11. <hi>As every man hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the gift, ſo miniſter the ſame one to another,</hi> as good ſtew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards of the manifold graces of God—that God may be glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified in all things through Jeſus Chriſt.] and not as an act of power; for no man hath <hi>dominion over another mans faith, but every one is bound to help another mans joy,</hi> 2 Cor. 1. 24.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, in the Manner of going about every work, two things muſt appeare—</p>
               <p>1. That it is undertaken in an orderly courſe, towards thoſe firſt that are chiefly concerned therein, and then towards others by degrees; without prepoſterouſneſſe and precipitancie.</p>
               <p>2. That the addreſſes which are made to every one of theſe in their proper places, are to be with all <hi>lowlineſſe, meekneſſe, long-ſuffering, and forbearance in love, to the end than the unity of the Spirit may be kept entire in the bond of Peace,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 12. 3. <hi>And all vain-glory, and provocation to ſtrife, and envy being avoyded,</hi> no offence may be given or taken at the work intended. <hi>Phil. 2. 3. Gal. 5. 26. 2 Cor.</hi> 6. 3, 4.</p>
               <p>Thus then we muſt conclude: that in all acts of Government if the work be defective in any of theſe properties, there wil either be no agreement at all, or no long continuance thereof. Therefore theſe generall Rules muſt have an influence upon all particular Deliberations and Reſolutions, to make them ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall. For the great point of difficulty in all acts of delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is this; To order a mans thoughts within himſelf, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:160191:29"/> a duty: And in the matter of Execution, the difficulty is this; To order a mans wayes towards others, ſo as to find ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance. Now by theſe Rules, by Gods aſſiſtance, all theſe difficulties may be overcome. As for the particular acts of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in themſelves, in admitting of Members to the Church, in ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing uſe of the Keyes of the Kingdome of Heaven, in adminiſtring the Seals of the Covenant, in overſeeing the Flock, and addreſſing or redreſſing them in their duties; they ought not ſuddenly and haſtily to be medled withall, till theſe Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals be well digeſted; for by the Method, which is in them preſcribed, they will prove ſucceſsfull. And in a word, nothing will ever be found commendable or warrantable, which in the undertaking, hath not a riſe from ſome cleer Rule in the Word; and in the application, is not proportionate to the capacity of thoſe to whom it is to be applied: for the Apoſtle doth inſtruct us by his example, to <hi>become all things to all men, to wiune ſome.</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 22.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Concerning the office and imployment of Deacon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</head>
               <p>1. THe name of a <hi>Deacon</hi> is diverſly taken in the Scripture; (the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) yet alwayes ſignifying one that is appointed for, or doth attend upon ſome ſervice: and according to the diverſity of the ſervice, the word is differently taken.</p>
               <p>2. Sometime it is applied to common ſervice; ſometime to peculiar ſervice to be performed in the Church only. It is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to common ſervice, <hi>Mat.</hi> 8. 15. where it is ſaid of <hi>Peters</hi> wives mother, that ſhe being cured of her fever, <hi>roſe</hi> and (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>miniſtred unto them.</hi> And in this ſenſe it is uſed, <hi>Mat. 20. 26. He that will be great among you, let him be your miniſter,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.)</p>
               <p>3. When it is applied to ſervice peculiarly belonging to the Church, it is again differently taken:</p>
               <p>Firſt, for the whole work which by Gods appointment is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:160191:30"/> to be performed in the Church, in all his Ordinances. So <hi>Chriſt</hi> is called, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. 8. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a Miniſter of the Circumciſion;</hi> ſo the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. 3, 4. doth call him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a Deacon of God, and his ſervice (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) a Deacon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; we render it Miniſtery: the words are, <hi>Giving none offence in any thing, that the Miniſtery (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) be not blamed, but in all things approving our ſelves as the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Deacons) of God.</hi> Here it takes in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Word with the other ſervice.</p>
               <p>Secondly, it is taken for that part of the Miniſtery which is contradiſtinct to the Adminiſtration of the Word, and ſtandeth wholly in matter of Action: in which ſenſe it is taken, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 6, 7. where the Apoſtle doth diſtribute all the offices belonging to the Church into two kinds, into <hi>Propheſie,</hi> and into (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) <hi>Miniſtery.</hi> By the firſt he meaneth the whole diſpenſation of the Word; and by the ſecond, all that which belongeth to matter of Action.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, it is taken moſt properly for that part of Action and Church-ſervice, which is diſtinct from the proper work of the Elders; and ſo it is here to be conſidered: and in this ſenſe the quality of a Deacon is deſcribed, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. from <hi>v.</hi> 8. till 14.</p>
               <p>4. This office was inſtituted by the Apoſtles at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to redreſſe an inconveniencie which did fall out in the <hi>daily mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ion;</hi> namely the <hi>neglect of</hi> ſome <hi>widowes</hi> more then of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; by reaſon of which inequality there aroſe a murmuring and diſcontent, which by theſe Officers was remedied, as you may read more at large, <hi>Acts 6. v.</hi> 1. till 7.</p>
               <p>5. The proper work then of the Deacons, is, To look to the proviſion which is made for the relief of the poor, that it be equally diſtributed according to their neceſſities; and to this effect, they are to receive and keep the collections which are made for that uſe; and they ought to viſit, and conſider the ſtate of the poor and ſick, that knowing their wants, the Elderſhip (and Congregation, if need be) may help to ſupply the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their ability.</p>
               <p>6. They ought in the work of their charge to be ſubordinate unto the Elderſhip, upon whom the chief care of the Flock doth
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:160191:30"/> lie: For, to eaſe the chief Elders at Jeruſalem, they were cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated: and the reaſon why they were conſtituted to eaſe them, is ſtill in force; for the text ſaith thus, <hi>Act. 6. 1. There aroſe a murmuring of the Grecians againſt the Hebrews, becauſe their widowes were neglected in the daily miniſtration.</hi> Verſ. 2. <hi>Then the Twelve called the multitude of the Diſciples unto them, and ſaid, it is not reaſon that we ſhould leave the word of God, and ſerve tables.</hi> v. 3. <hi>Wherefore brethren, look ye out among you ſeven men of honeſt report, full of the Holy Ghoſt and wiſdome, whom we may appoint over this buſineſſe;</hi> v. 4. <hi>But we will give our ſelves continually to prayer, and the miniſtry of the Word.</hi> From whence it appeareth, that the ſervice of tables (that is, to provide meat for the poor, and diſtribute unto them their portion) is not to be impoſed upon them that attend the labour of the Word and Prayer, but ought to be committed unto ſome others. And that theſe others are ſubordinate unto them, appeareth both by the nature of their imployment, which is about a matter of lower concernment; and by the manner of their admiſſion unto it, which was by the impoſition of the hands of the Elderſhip: for the Apoſtles did appoint them to their office, not only as Apoſtles, but as Elders of that congregation.</p>
               <p>7. And becauſe they are thus ſubordinate unto the Elderſhip by their primitive conſtitution; therefore in the Reformed churches they are obliged to regulate their matters by the adviſe of the Elderſhip, to whom they are bound from time to time to ſhew the accounts of their receipts and disburſments, and the condition of the poor who are to be relieved. [In the Synodical Acts of the French churches, <hi>cap.</hi> 4. and in the Church-Orders of the Dutch-churches, <hi>art.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>8. And becauſe they are thus accountable unto the Elderſhip, they are bound to keep exact reckonings of their receipts and disburſements. The Receipts come, in Foraigne churches, chiefly in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> onely from free willing contributions, which at every meeting of the Congregation to heare the Word, are gathered by the Deacons; and the Disburſements are indifferently to all the Poore who offer themſelves, but chiefly to thoſe of their owne Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:160191:31"/>
               <p>9. In larger Congregations of the Foraign churches, the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip hath their meeting apart from the Deacons, &amp; the Deacons meet ordinarily by themſelves once or twice a week; but in leſſer Congregations, the Elders and Deacons meet ordinarily all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether at leaſt once a week.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Concerning the Duty of Chriſtians, as they are to be in a particular Church, and under the government of Rulers ſet over them in the Lord.</head>
               <p>1. WE underſtand by Chriſtians, men that have given up their names unto Chriſt, to be called (<hi>a</hi>) by his name, (<hi>a</hi>) Act. 11. 26. <hi>The Diſciples were called Chriſtians firſt in Antioch.</hi> &amp; Epheſ. 3. 15. <hi>Of whom the family in heaven and earth is named;</hi> to call (<hi>b</hi>) upon him, (<hi>b</hi>) 1 Cor. 1. 2. <hi>All that in every place call upon the name of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>] by calling him (<hi>c</hi>) their Lord, (<hi>c</hi>) 1 Cor. 12. 3. <hi>No man can ſay that Jeſus Chriſt is the Lord, but by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>2. By a <hi>Church,</hi> is meant a congregation of ſuch men called and gathered together by the Word; <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 37. till 44. to be (<hi>d</hi>) ſeparate from the world, (<hi>d</hi>) 2 Cor. 6. 17. <hi>Come out from them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord, and I will receive you.</hi> &amp; Revel. 18. 4. <hi>Come out of her</hi> (viz. of Babylon) <hi>my people</hi>] and in the uſe of all <hi>Chriſts ordinances, to be an habitation of God through the Spirit,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 19, 20, 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 22.</p>
               <p>3. The duty of Chriſtians as viſible profeſſors of Chriſtianity; doth ſtand in a threefold Relation:</p>
               <p>The firſt is to the Church, as it is the Body of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The ſecond is to the Elderſhip of that Church.</p>
               <p>The third is to the Members thereof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Of the firſt,</hi> viz. <hi>Duties relating to the Body of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>4. All Chriſtians that glory in the name of Chriſt, ought to appeare (<hi>e</hi>) for him amongſt men, (<hi>e</hi>) Matth. 10. 32, 33. <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſhall confeſſe me before men, him will I confeſſe alſo before my
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:160191:31"/> Father which is in heaven; but whoſoever ſhall deny me before men, him will I alſo deny before my Father which is in heaven.</hi>] And they ought ſo to appeare as he hath appointed, and not as they think good, or as men appoint. Mat. 15. 9. <hi>In vain do they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip me, teaching for doctrines the commandements of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>5. Thoſe that will appeare for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ought to apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to ſome particular Congregation profeſſing Saintſhip, as Members thereof. Mat. 12. 30. <hi>He that is not with me, is againſt me, and he that gathereth not with me, ſcattereth abroad.</hi> Mat. 11. 28, 29. <hi>Come unto me—take my yoke upon you.</hi> Gal. 6. 10. <hi>Them who are of the houſhold of faith.</hi> 1 Joh. 2. 19. <hi>They went out from us, but they were not of us,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 8. 16. <hi>Binde up the Teſtimony, and ſeale the Law among my diſciples.</hi> 1 Cor. 1, 2. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church of God which is at Corinth, to them that are ſanctified—called to be Saints.</hi> &amp; 1 Cor. 12. 27. <hi>Ye are members in particular.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>6. It is foretold, that there ſhould be many Congregations in the Church of the Goſpel, and yet all upon the ſame Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and under the ſame defence; and by Gods appointment to be as one Body, Iſa. 4. 5. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon every dwelling place of mount Zion, and upon her aſſemblies, there ſhall be a cloud and ſmoak by day, and the burning of a flaming fire by night.</hi> Joh. 10. 16. <hi>Other ſheep, not of this fold, them I muſt bring—there ſhall be one fold and one ſhepherd.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>7. Now to underſtand the Relation which believing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours have unto the Church, three things are to be conſidered. Firſt, how every Believer doth ſtand, as to a particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. Secondly, how one Congregation doth ſtand as to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, in reſpect both of the Members and of the Rulers thereof. And thirdly, how Believers ſhould apply themſelves unto par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregations, and be received therein by their Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips.</p>
               <p>8. All Believers <hi>are baptized by one: Spirit into one Body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Of the firſt head; how be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers stand in a particular congregation.</note> 1 Cor. 12, 13. and in that one Body they are called to the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment <hi>of the Peace of God,</hi> Coloſſ. 3. 15. and therein by God <hi>ſet in their</hi> ſeverall <hi>places,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. 18. and <hi>made members one of another,</hi> Rom. 12. 4, 5. and <hi>joyned</hi> and <hi>compacted together by joynts under their head Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 16. whoſe Body is
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:160191:32"/> every congregation of believers, 1 Cor. 12. 27. <hi>Now ye</hi> (viz. Corinthians) <hi>are the Body of Chriſt,</hi> Rom. 12. 5. <hi>So we</hi> (viz. Romans) <hi>are one Body in Chriſt.</hi> And the Church univerſall, Epheſ. 1. 22, 23. <hi>the head over all things to the Church, which is his Body, the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>9. From hence it is evident, that every believer is not only bound to make open profeſſion of his faith, (as is (<hi>f</hi>) required <hi>Rom. 10. 9, 10.) (f) If thou confeſſe with thy mouth the Lord Jeſus, and ſhalt believe in thine heart that God hath raiſed him from the dead, thou ſhalt be ſaved. For with the heart man believeth unto righteouſneſſe, and with the mouth confeſſion is made unto ſalvation.</hi>] but that in ſo doing he is bound to appeare in the communion of (<hi>g</hi>) Saints, <hi>ſtanding in one body faſt together with</hi> others, &amp; <hi>ſtriving for the Faith of the Goſpel,</hi> Phil. 1, 27. (<hi>g</hi>) Ph. 2. 1, 2, 4. <hi>If there be any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of love, if any fellowſhip of the Spirit—be ye like-minded, having the ſame love, being of one accord, of one mind; look not every man on his own things, but every man alſo on the things of others.</hi>] And by this conjunction of Believers, when an Elderſhip is rightly ſet over them, particular Congregations are conſtituted. As <hi>Act.</hi> 14. 22, 23. The Apoſtles having converted the Gentiles to the faith, <hi>ordained them Elders in every Church,</hi> with prayer and faſting.</p>
               <p>10. As ſingle Believers are bound to aſſociate themſelves one to<note place="margin">Of the ſecond head, how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations doe ſtand one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</note> another; ſo ought every congregation of Believers to aſſociate it ſelf to its neighbour-congregation by the very ſame rules &amp; bands by which particular Chriſtians are bound to joyn themſelves one to another. For if <hi>all</hi> Believers in the world <hi>are baptized into one Body, 1 Cor.</hi> 12. 13. and if all are <hi>called to the Peace of God in that one Body, Col.</hi> 3. 15. and are bound to <hi>endeavour the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit one towards another, in the Bond of that Peace,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is but <hi>one Body of Chriſt</hi> in all the world, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 1, 2, 3, 4. which is homogeneall (that is, of the ſame kinde) in all the members thereof: And if this <hi>whole Body</hi> is to <hi>be fitly joyned and compacted together by that which every joint ſupplieth, Epheſ.</hi> 4. 16. Then ought none of all the congregations of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers to ſtand ſeparate one from another, but are bound to unite themſelves by their joynts (that is their Officers) ſo neer as poſſibly they can, in all Spirituall relations, for their <hi>mutuall edification in love,</hi> Epheſ. 4. 16.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:160191:32"/>
               <p>11. So then, every true Believer that hath made open pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion<note place="margin">In reſpect of their Members.</note> of his faith, by being a member of any one Congregation, hath a right of memberſhip unto all the congregations of the world, becauſe all are <hi>but one in Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 3. 28. and all have <hi>one and the ſame acceſſe unto the Father,</hi> and are <hi>fellow-citizens,</hi> and of the <hi>ſame houſhold of Faith,</hi> Epheſ. 2. 19.</p>
               <p>12. It is then contrary to the mind of Chriſt, that thoſe who make profeſſion of the ſame faith, and worſhip in the ſame way, ſhould ſtand either ſingle by themſelves, and not imbodyed with other profeſſors; or ſtand ſo imbodyed with ſome, as to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynted from other bodies of the ſame profeſſion.</p>
               <p>13. Nor ought any Church-officers to take upon them ſuch a<note place="margin">In reſpect of their Officers.</note> Relation to any particular Body, as to think themſelves obliged unto none but unto the members thereof, in their Miniſteriall charges; for if they do ſo, they make themſelves to be no joints in the body of Chriſt, (which every officer is bound to be) and they hinder the <hi>compacting of the whole together,</hi> which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the end of their imployment, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 13. 16. and they open a door to the <hi>cunning craftineſſe</hi> of <hi>men who lie in wait to deceive;</hi> that it <hi>may ſeduce the ſimple and plain-hearted believer, and unſettle him.</hi> Epheſ. 4. 14. Rom. 16. 18.</p>
               <p>14. All Chriſtians applying themſelves unto a particular<note place="margin">Of the third head, how be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers ſhould apply them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation.</note> congregation, ought to come thereunto free, <hi>willingly, in the beauty of holineſſe,</hi> Pſal. 110. 3. and not upon any other conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations then the love of Holineſſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.</p>
               <p>15. If any that are eminent in the world, do ſtand upon the points of Honour, thinking that they have a right to the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of the kingdom of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by reaſon of their places in the world; and that it would be unbeſeeming to them to offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be admitted into a particular congregation: They do greatly miſtake the nature of Gods kingdom, &amp; the ſtate of true Honour; for none are truly excellent &amp; honourable but (<hi>h</hi>) Saints, (<hi>h</hi>) Pſal. 16. 3. <hi>The Saints that are in the earth, and to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent in whom is all my delight</hi>] and the Godly, <hi>whom God hath ſet apart for himſelf,</hi> Pſal. 4. 2, 3. Now the <hi>Kingdome of Chriſt is not of this world,</hi> Ioh. 18. 37. nor can it be entertained with the worldly reſpects (<hi>i</hi>) of perſons, (<hi>i</hi>) Jam. 2. 1, 2. <hi>My brethren, have not the faith of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt the Lord of glory,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:160191:33"/> with reſpect of perſons; For if there come into your Aſſembly a man with a gold ring in goodly apparell, and there come in alſo a poore man in vile raiment,</hi> v. 3. <hi>and ye have reſpect to him that weareth the gay cloathing, and ſay unto him, Sit thou here in a good place, and ſay to the poor, Stand thou there, or ſit here under my footſtoole,</hi> v. 4. <hi>are ye not then partiall in your ſelves, and become judges of evill thoughts?</hi>] Becauſe the world, and all that is in it, is either wholly oppoſite (<hi>k</hi>) unto Chriſtianity, and <hi>doth lie in wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 19. (<hi>k</hi>) Gal. 6. 14. <hi>But God forbid that I ſhould glory ſave in the croſſe of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt; by whom the world is crucified unto me, and I unto the world.</hi> &amp; 1 Cor. 3. 19. <hi>The wiſdome of this world is fooliſhneſſe with God.</hi>] or elſe, at the beſt, (<hi>l</hi>) ſubordinate unto it. (<hi>l</hi>) &amp; 1 Cor. 3. 22. <hi>whether Paul, or Apollos, or Cephas, or the world, or life, or death, or things pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, or things to come, all are yours, and ye are Chriſts, and Chriſt is Gods.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Chriſt is ſubordinate unto God, ye are ſubordinate unto Chriſt, the world and all things in it are ſubordinate to your uſe in reference to Chriſt. Therefore it can be no diſparagement to any in the world to apply themſelves to Chriſt in his ordinances; but it will be their greateſt honour, to exalt him; for ſuch as <hi>confeſſe him before men, he will confeſſe before his heavenly Father and his holy Angels,</hi> Mat. 10. 32. Luk. 12. 8.</p>
               <p>16. Nor do the Saints by their profeſſion of being ſeparate from the world, make voyd any of the lawes of nature; becauſe they are commanded to be <hi>ſubject unto every ordinance of man for the Lords ſake,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 13. And the Lord of glory himſelfe (though not bound) did ſubmit, by paying tribute, unto the ordinance of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> Mat. 17. 24, 25, 26, 27. and <hi>hath commanded all to give unto Caeſar what is Caeſars, and unto God what is Gods,</hi> Mat. 22. 15. till <hi>v.</hi> 22. Now to <hi>Caeſar</hi> is due (<hi>m</hi>) ſubmiſſion, and (<hi>n</hi>) honour. (<hi>m</hi>) Rom. 13. 1. <hi>Let every ſoule be ſubject to the Higher powers.</hi> &amp; 1 Pet. 2. 13. <hi>Submit your ſelves—unto the King as ſupreme, or unto Governours as unto them that are ſent by him. (n</hi>) 1 Pet. 2. 17. <hi>Honour the King.</hi>] As then by the Kingdom of Chriſt, none of the great ones of the world loſe any reſpect due unto them, but rather receive an increaſe of Honour; ſo they ought not to refuſe to yield unto Chriſt the reſpect
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:160191:33"/> which is due unto Him, and his Kingdom; for by giving them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves up to it, they are ſet above themſelves, that is, out of the world and the reſpects of it.</p>
               <p>17. Every one then that will be called a Chriſtian (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever they are amongſt men, it maketh no matter, God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepteth no mans perſon) is bound as a Chriſtian to offer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to be imbodyed into a Congregation, and to partake of the priviledges of the houſhold of Faith, and ought profeſſedly to (<hi>o</hi>) ſubject himſelf unto the Goſpel, (<hi>o</hi>) 2 Cor. 9. 13. <hi>They glorifie God for your profeſſed ſubjection unto the Goſpel of Chriſt.</hi>] and give (<hi>p</hi>) himſelf over unto the Lord, and by the will of God unto that Elderſhip whereunto he doth make his applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. (<hi>p</hi>) 2 Cor. 8. 5. <hi>They gave their own ſelves unto the Lord, and unto us, by the will of God.</hi> &amp; Act. 2. 41, 42. <hi>There was added</hi> (viz. unto the Church) <hi>three thouſand ſoules; and they continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apostles doctrine, and fellowſhip, and in breaking of bread, and in prayers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>18. Such as offer themſelves in this manner unto the Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,<note place="margin">And how they ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived therein.</note> ought to be received without much (<hi>q</hi>) difficulty or ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puloſity, (<hi>q</hi>) Rom. 14. 1. <hi>Him that is weak in the Faith, receive you, but not to doubtfull diſputations.</hi>] even as Chriſt (<hi>r</hi>) received us, (<hi>r</hi>) Rom. 15. 7. <hi>Receive ye one another, as Chriſt alſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived us to the glory of God.</hi>] And ſuch as <hi>come to him,</hi> he ſaith <hi>he will in no wiſe caſt out,</hi> Joh. 6. 37.</p>
               <p>19. Now concerning the outward form and manner of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting Profeſſors unto the holy Communion, and diſtinguiſhing them from thoſe that are without; we find nothing diſtinctly enjoyned in the Word, or extant in the practice of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles: Therefore that which may concern this matter, is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived to be left free unto the diſcretion of the Elderſhip, as they ſhall think it moſt fit, for the edification and capacity of thoſe with whom they have to do.</p>
               <p>And herein the cuſtomes of the Reformed churches, in reſpect of circumſtantials, are found to be different; yet, in the main, their agreement is this—</p>
               <p>1. That every one who for the firſt time is to be admitted unto the Holy communion, is to be examined in reſpect of his knowledge and converſation; although from his infancie he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:160191:34"/> hath been borne, baptized, and bred in the Congregation.</p>
               <p>2. If he come from abroad; having years of diſcretion and judgement fit to examine himſelf, it is expected he ſhould have a teſtimoniall of his former life and converſation, and of his diligence in attending the Ordinances in the place where he hath lived. And being found knowing in the fundamentall truths of Chriſtianity, he is deſired</p>
               <p>Firſt, to declare that his purpoſe is to live and die in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Reformed churches.</p>
               <p>Secondly, to promiſe, that if he ſhould conceive any ſcruples of the Doctrine that is taught in the Reformed churches, he ſhall not conceale his doubts, and fall away from the Fellowſhip into which he is received; but make the ſame known unto his Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, to receive ſatisfaction therein.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, to oblige himſelf to uſe all carefull diligence to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and adorn his profeſſion with his life and converſation, and to avoyd all occaſion of ſcandall.</p>
               <p>Fourthly and laſtly, to promiſe to ſubmit himſelf unto the Rules of Church-diſcipline, according to the Word; and to reſpect thoſe that are ſet over him in the Lord.</p>
               <p>All which he is engaged to do by word of mouth, and by giving his hand unto the Elderſhip.</p>
               <p>In ſome places, this admiſſion of Members is left to the Paſtor, to be performed in private; yet ſo, as the reception of the party muſt be notified unto, and ratified by the Elderſhip. In ſome places, all is done before the whole Elderſhip. In ſome places alſo, the names of thoſe that are admitted, are publiſhed unto the whole Congregation from the Pulpit.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the ſecond, <hi>viz.</hi> Duties relating to the Elderſhip.</head>
                  <p>20. Such as have given up their names unto a Congregation to be under a Paſtorall charge, and the government of an Elder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, ought to hear (<hi>s</hi>) the voice of their Paſtors, (<hi>s</hi>) Joh. 10. 3. <hi>The ſheep hear his voice.</hi>] To (<hi>t</hi>) follow them, (<hi>t</hi>) Ibid. v. 4. <hi>The ſheep follow him, for they know his voice.</hi>] To continue (<hi>u</hi>) in their fellowſhip, and not to follow ſtrangers, (<hi>u</hi>) Act. 2. 42. <hi>They continued ſtedfaſtly in the Apoſtles doctrine and fellowſhip.</hi>]
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:160191:34"/> Yet by this they are not deprived of the liberty of hearing others beſides their own Paſtors, that they may (<hi>x</hi>) prove all things, and hold faſt that which is good, (<hi>x</hi>) 1 Theſſ 5. 21. <hi>Prove all things, hold faſt that which is good.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>21. They ought to obey their Rulers (<hi>y</hi>) &amp; ſubmit themſelves unto them; that their work may be done with joy, and not with grief, (<hi>y</hi>) Heb. 13. 17. <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves, for they watch—That they may do it with joy, and not with grief.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>22. This obedience and ſubmiſſion ought not to be formall, but hearty, proceeding from (<hi>z</hi>) a high eſteem of them in love for their works ſake, (<hi>z</hi>) 1 Theſſ. 5. 13. <hi>Eſteem them</hi> (viz. thoſe that labour, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you) <hi>very highly in love for their works ſake.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>23. As an inward affection and eſteem, ſo an outward care for their Rulers is requiſite in Profeſſors: They ought then to <hi>communicate unto thoſe that teach them in all good things,</hi> Gal. 6. 6. counting all that Rule well, <hi>worthy of double honour; but eſpecially</hi> to provide maintenance for <hi>thoſe that labour in the word and doctrine,</hi> 1 Tim. 5. 17. becauſe the Lord hath ordained <hi>that thoſe who preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel,</hi> 1 Cor. 9. 14.</p>
                  <p>24. They ought <hi>to mark and avoyd all Teachers that cauſe offences and diviſions amongſt them,</hi> Rom. 16.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of the third, <hi>viz.</hi> Duties relating to their Fellow-members.</head>
                  <p>25. They ought to conſider their fellow-members; to <hi>provoke them to love and to good works; not forſaking the aſſembling of themſelves together, as the manner of ſome is.</hi> Heb. 10. 24, 25.</p>
                  <p>26. They ought to <hi>hold forth the word of life, and ſhine as lights in the world in the midſt of a crooked generation,</hi> Phil. 2. 15.</p>
                  <p>27. To this effect they ought to do all things without <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings and diſputings, that they may be found blameleſſe as the children of God,</hi> Phil. 2. 4.</p>
                  <p>28. They ought to <hi>ſerve their brethren through love,</hi> Gal. 5. 13. and <hi>not to pleaſe themſelves, but others for their good to edification,</hi> Rom. 15. 1, 2.</p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:160191:35"/>
                  <p>29. They ought not either to <hi>deſpiſe</hi> or <hi>judge</hi> one another for matters which God hath left free, either to be done, or not to be done, according as God doth give every one the meaſure of faith. <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. the whole chap.</p>
                  <p>30. They ought to <hi>withdraw themſelves from every brother that walketh diſorderly and is a buſie body,</hi> 2 Theſſ. 3. 6, 11. yet they ought not to <hi>count him an enemy, but ſhould admoniſh him as a Brother.</hi> ibid. v. 15.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Certain Rules concerning the Adminiſtration of the LORDS Supper, for the decent ordering of the action. Offered to the conſideration of thoſe that ſcruple at the geſture of Sitting.</head>
               <p>1. IT is not lawfull for us, in Gods worſhip, to do what we think good in our own eyes; but what is moſt agreeable to his will.</p>
               <p>2. For if we know not what his will is, we cannot worſhip him in Faith.</p>
               <p>3. If we worſhip him not in faith, we cannot pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>4. And if we pleaſe him not, we cannot expect a bleſſing upon our performance.</p>
               <p>5. Therefore to be ſure of a bleſſing, we muſt know and carefully obſerve that which is moſt anſwerable to his will, in things belonging to his worſhip.</p>
               <p>6. Now to know and obſerve this in the Sacrament of the Lords ſupper; Chriſts practiſe in the inſtitution thereof, ſo far as he would have us to imitate the ſame, and his intention in commanding us to imitate him therein, is to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>7. The neceſſity of conſidering Chriſts practiſe and intention in this matter, doth ariſe from the Apoſtles commandement, who doth herein very diſtinctly referre us unto Chriſt himſelfe for a warrant of that which is to be done; ſaying, that in this matter, he <hi>delivered that which he received of the Lord,</hi> 1 Cor. 11. 23. and that we ought <hi>to follow him ſo far as he is a follower of the Lord,</hi> ibid. v. 1.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:160191:35"/>
               <p>8. Therefore we are bound to look unto Chriſt in the firſt place; and to the Apoſtles afterward, with a reference unto the Lord: becauſe finally our faith muſt reſt only in the Lord, as the object thereof; and the end and uſe of the Apoſtolicall miniſtery is, to call us unto communion with them; that by them <hi>we may have communion with the Father, and with his ſonne Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1 Joh. 1. 3. For we are ſure, that in following him and fulfilling his intention, we do nothing amiſſe; becauſe He is <hi>the Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> Joh. 14. 6.</p>
               <p>9. Chriſts practiſe then in the inſtitution of his Supper, in that which is to be imitated, is this—</p>
               <p>Firſt, he took the Bread, and by giving ſpeciall thanks over it, he ſeparated it from the common to a holy uſe; then he brake it, and gave it to his diſciples, and commanded them to eat thereof.</p>
               <p>Secondly, he took the Cup, which in like manner by a ſpeciall bleſſing he ſeparated from the common to a holy uſe; and then gave it to his Diſciples, commanding them all to drink of it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, this bread and cup the Lord did diſtribute being at the table with his Diſciples, where he ſpake with them of his death and of the fruits thereof, and of his comming again, as you may ſee more at large in <hi>Matth.</hi> 26. from <hi>verſ.</hi> 20. till 36. <hi>Mark</hi> 14. from <hi>v.</hi> 18. till 32. <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. from <hi>v.</hi> 13. till 39. and in <hi>John,</hi> the whole chapters, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17. are to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the other three Evangeliſts, and taken in as the matter of his table-diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>10. Next unto this practiſe of the Lord, the Apoſtolicall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, which in the Primitive church did herein follow the Lord, is conſiderable; that we may obſerve thereby what is properly imitable in the Lords practiſe, by the Church.</p>
               <p>11. Let us look upon that which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> delivereth unto the church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> Epiſt. 1. chap. 10, 11. I ſhall open the places briefly, and then make ſome obſervations upon them.</p>
               <p>In <hi>chap.</hi> 10. the Apoſtles ſcope is, to diſſwade the Corinthians from ſymbolizing with Idolaters in eating of things ſacrificed unto idols. The parts of the chapter are two: Firſt, he forbids a mixt communion with Idolaters in things pertaining to their Idol-worſhip, as ſuch; from <hi>v.</hi> 1. till 23. Secondly, he permits
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:160191:36"/> unto them a mixt converſation with Idolaters, in eating and drinking even of thoſe things which they had offered unto idols, with this caution, if it were done without offence unto weaker brethren, from <hi>v.</hi> 23. till the end.</p>
               <p>Amongſt other arguments uſed to diſſwade them from par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking with idolaters in their Idol-worſhip, one is taken from their engagement to celebrate the Lords ſupper, and from the relation which they had to the Lord in it, and to one another. This is expreſſed from <hi>v.</hi> 15. till 22. where firſt he ſtirs them up to attention, and to a ſerious conſideration of that which he was to ſay. <hi>I ſpeak as to wiſe men</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>judge ye what I ſay,</hi> v. 15. Then he declareth unto them three things; and by the anſwer of a doubt, doth conclude his dehortation.</p>
               <p>Firſt he ſheweth what is meant by the uſe of the Elements in the Lords ſupper. <hi>The cup of bleſſing</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which we bleſſe, is it not the communion of the blood of Chriſt? and the bread which we breake, is it not the communion of the body of Chriſt?</hi> verſ. 16. As if he had ſaid, What do you mean by bleſſing the cup, and breaking the bread at the Lords ſupper? for what end and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is it inſtituted? Is it not to evidence that you have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with Chriſt in his body and blood, as his ſpirituall mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers belonging to him?</p>
               <p>Secondly he ſheweth what is meant by their joynt partaking of the Elements. <hi>We being many</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>are one bread, and one body; for we are all partakers of that one bread,</hi> v. 17. As if he had ſaid; although in our ſelves we are many and diſtinct per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, yet in reference to Chriſt we are (as of old the ſhew-bread was to the Lord) but one bread, and one myſticall body; becauſe we all jointly do partake of that one bread which in a myſterie is his body. And this is brought in as a reaſon to confirme the foregoing point; <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we being many, are one bread,</hi> &amp;c. that is, The reaſon why the bleſſing of the cup and breaking of the bread doth mean and import a communion with Chriſt in his blood &amp; body, is cleer from our mutual relation and the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction wherein we ſtand one to another, by this action jointly performed; which is this: That we all by it reſpecting each other in Chriſt, evidence our ſelves to be one bread and one body to him. So then hereby we plainly atteſt our communion with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:160191:36"/> him, ſeeing by this action, as relating unto him, we have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion one with another.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, he ſheweth what is meant by the eating of Sacrifices. v. 18. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Iſrael after the fleſh; are not they which eat of the ſacrifices, partakers of the altar?</hi> As if he had ſaid: conſider the cuſtome of the Jews after the fleſh in their ſacrifices, and the ordinance that God gave unto them concerning the eat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of holy things: Their cuſtome is, that ſuch as eat of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, have communion with the Altar, and partake in the worſhip by which the ſacrifices are offered up unto God; and if you look upon Gods ordinance given to the Prieſts concerning holy things, <hi>Levit.</hi> 22. from <hi>v.</hi> 10. till 17. you ſhall ſee that all ſtrangers are expreſly forbidden to partake thereof, and that none but ſuch as had a reference to the altar might eat of them; the Lord intimating, and the cuſtome of the Nation confirming it, that the eating of ſacrifices is not a common action, but a matter of worſhip importing a communion with the Altar.</p>
               <p>From all which the Apoſtle doth tacitely inſinuate thus much: That as the chief thing aimed at in the Lords ſupper, is to evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence our communion with Chriſt, and with one another in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to him; and the cleer purpoſe of the Jews in eating of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, was to manifeſt their relation unto the Altar as partakers of the worſhip and ſervice done at it; So the meaning and intent of eating things ſacrificed unto Idols, muſt be, to have communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the altar of the Idol, and the idolatrous worſhip per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed thereat. This inference is not expreſſed, but only inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated, till a doubt be propoſed and anſwered.</p>
               <p>The doubt is propoſed <hi>v.</hi> 19. thus: <hi>What ſay L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that the Idol is any thing? or that which is offered <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n ſacrifice to Idols is any thing?</hi> As if he had ſaid: I do not intend to intimate unto you by this, that an Idol is that which hath a reall being; <hi>for we know that an Idol is nothing in the world,</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 4, 8. conſequently, I do not ſay that the things offered in ſacrifice unto Idols are any thing in reference to worſhip, further then the imagination of the Idolater doth fancie them to be; which giveth no being to any thing. So then in the propoſall of the doubt, he doth cleerly deny that which it ſeemeth to ſuppoſe; and then for a fuller anſwer unto it, he doth ſhew his cleer
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:160191:37"/> meaning concerning the ſacrifices of the Gentiles, and inferreth from thence as a concluſion, that their duty was, not to partake thereof.</p>
               <p>His meaning concerning the ſacrifices of the Gentiles, is, <hi>v.</hi> 20. in theſe words: <hi>But I ſay that the things which the Gentiles ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, they ſacrifice unto devils</hi> (Demons) <hi>and not unto God.</hi> As if he had ſaid; But my meaning is, to declare that the purpoſe of the Gentiles is to worſhip their Demons, which are Devils, or imaginary, and not the true Gods.</p>
               <p>Whereupon he inferreth his dehortatory concluſion thus: <hi>And I would not that ye ſhould have fellowſhip with devils.</hi> As if he ſaid; Becauſe the meaning and purpoſe of partaking of Sacrifices, is to have communion in Worſhip; and it is evident that the Gentiles do worſhip Demons, which are devils, or ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginary gods; therefore I diſſwade you from having any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with them. And he giveth the reaſon why he doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade them from this, <hi>v.</hi> 21. in theſe words: <hi>Ye cannot drink the cup of the Lord, and the cup of Devils; ye cannot be partakers of the Lords table, and of the table of Devils;</hi> As if he had ſaid, I diſſwade you from this, becauſe you cannot ſtand under two oppoſite relations, and have communion with two oppoſites at one and the ſame time. The relation which you have unto Chriſt, and their relation to the Devils, are oppoſite; therefore you cannot ſtand under both at once, you cannot maintain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with both at once; but if you partake of the cup and table of the one, you muſt abſtain from the cup and table of the other.</p>
               <p>13. Thus having opened the words; the obſervations which I will briefly make upon them, are theſe—</p>
               <p>Firſt, we may gather from hence, that to ſymbolize with Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters in their acts of worſhip, is a thing unlawfull to Chriſtians. We know that the Maſſe is the greateſt idol that ever was in the world; and that the act of kneeling was brought in at the Popiſh communion to worſhip that Idol: we ought not therefore to ſymbolize with them in that act of worſhip; for it is not lawfull for us to follow the corruption of an Ordinance, when we have Chriſts imitable practiſe made known to us: It is not lawfull to mixe the acts of Gods true worſhip, with the chief act
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:160191:37"/> of an Idol-worſhip, ſuch as is Kneeling at the <hi>Maſſe;</hi> For the meaning and purpoſe of kneeling, is Adoration; the object of adoration is the Body and blood of Chriſt, ſuppoſed to be in the Elements: but if we believe no ſuch reall preſence as they have fancied, then we make void the object of adoration, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the act intended towards it is diſanulled alſo. But if any doth incline to kneeling, becauſe it hath been a cuſtome hitherto uſed; he may upon the ſame ground practiſe all other Popiſh idolatries and ſuperſtitions. But if you will ſay, that you think Chriſt ought to be worſhipped there, and that you cannot come to his table with too much reverence; You muſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that Chriſt doth not intend to be worſhipped there, but to be received; and that you muſt not be led by your own think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, but by the manifeſtation of his will in matters of worſhip; nor can any one geſture be accounted reverence to him more then another, otherwiſe then as he doth appoint it to be in his worſhip. The ſtanding at the firſt Paſſeover in Egypt, was a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence; The ſitting at the table with Chriſt, was in his diſciples a reverence to him; nay, and their ſuffering of him to waſh their feet, as their ſervant, was a reverence due to him as their maſter, becauſe it was his will to have it ſo. It is neither circumciſion nor uncircumciſion, but the doing of Gods will, that maketh us acceptable unto him. Now it is contrary to his will, that we ſhould follow another example of worſhip then that which his Apoſtles have given us: It is contrary to his will, that we in his worſhip ſhould ſymbolize with Idolaters, and that we ſhould ſeem to collude with them in their act of Idol-worſhip, when we know that the Lord will not be adored, but received in his Supper; and it is no reverence at all, but a very irreverent and unbeſeeming behaviour, to put forth an act proper to adoration, when he doth call us to put forth an act of communion and fellowſhip.</p>
               <p>The ſecond obſervation is; That the eating of bread, and drinking of a cup at the Lords ſupper, is a Table-action. This is to be gathered from <hi>verſ. 17. We are partakers of one Bread; &amp; v. 21. Partakers of the table of the Lord, and of the table of Devils.</hi> Theſe expreſſions are here uſed with a reference to the aime of fellowſhip and communion: whence I inferre theſe concluſions.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:160191:38"/>
               <p>1. Seeing the act of Communion is to be evidenced chiefly by the partaking of one Bread by many; it doth follow, that the more that bread, and the partaking of it is one, the more the act of communion is evidenced. Then it followeth alſo, that the partaking of the bread ought to be as much one, as the nature of a Meal doth permit, and as Chriſt by his example doth inſinuate. Now the nature of a Meal, doth not only permit, but require, that ſuch as have fellowſhip in it, ſhould be together as gueſts to partake jointly of it; and Chriſts example doth cleerly ſhew that all his Diſciples were in fellowſhip together with him at a table. And therefore to partake of one bread, and of the Lords table, muſt be underſtood to be ſuch a table-action as is proper unto gueſts at a table. From whence it will follow, that to carry the bread and wine up and down the houſe, to perſons ſitting in ſeverall pewes, as in ſo many little chambers of that houſe, is not at all ſutable to the celebrating of the Lords ſupper, becauſe it doth wholly take away the manifeſtation of that fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip which the Lord would have evidenced in it. Thoſe that eat their bread apart, in ſeverall petty corporations, do not ſhew forth that they are one bread; as the Shewbread was, which was to be ſet before the Lord upon the holy table in the Sanctuary, <hi>Exod. 25. 30. &amp; Levit. 24. v.</hi> 5. till 10. Which Bread did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the whole Congregation of <hi>Iſrael</hi> united as one unto the Lord, in twelve cakes ſet upon one table; which type is now fulfilled in the Goſpel, by the joynt preſentation of the reall members of Chriſt as one bread at his table, to his Father, to be a living ſacrifice unto him. Nor can it be ſaid that thoſe who ſit in their pewes at a diſtance from each other, are one Body, as men uſe to be at Meales; for at meales none are one body pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, but ſuch as eat together at the ſame table: Therefore this cuſtome is not ſutable to that which is to be evidenced at the partaking of the Lords table.</p>
               <p>2. To ſhew an act of Communion, we muſt partake of the Bread as it is one. Now the bread is not one otherwiſe then as it is upon the ſame table, and bleſſed with the ſame Bleſſing: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it will follow, that the partaking of it as one, muſt be to receive it at the table, in a table-action: For if a Table is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to ſhew that we are to be at Chriſts ſupper as his gueſts;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:160191:38"/> and if it be asked what Chriſt would have his gueſts to do? the anſwer muſt be taken from <hi>Luke</hi> 22. 30. That he would have them <hi>eat and drink with him at table in his Kingdome.</hi> To eat and drink (then) at his table, is to be his gueſt; and not to have a bit of meat brought from the table. If <hi>Lazarus</hi> the begger lying at the rich mans gate, had received a diſh of meat from his table, it would not have made him one of his gueſts: but the other <hi>Lazarus</hi> of <hi>Bethany</hi> who ſate with Chriſt at table <hi>Joh.</hi> 2. 2. was properly a fellow-gueſt (or perhaps Chriſts hoſt) becauſe he did eat with him at the table. To have fellowſhip then in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of the table, is to be at the table, and to do the action proper to a table: But to carry the bread and drink from the table, to give it to every one apart, is contrary to this Table<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, and therefore not to be practiſed any longer, in this time of Reformation.</p>
               <p>3. The table of the Lord, and the table of Devils, are ſet as parallel in oppoſition to each other; therefore to partake of the one, and of the other, are made contraries directly incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent together; and being actions directly contrary, they muſt be of one kind; and if of one kind, then the table-action uſed at the one, was the ſame with the action uſed at the other. Now it is known that at the Idol-ſacrifices, ſuch as were invited, did ſit and feaſt at a table, 1 <hi>Cor. 8. 10. Sit at meat in the Idols temple.</hi> And it was the cuſtom of all ages to have a feaſt upon a ſacrifice; you may ſee it at <hi>Jacob</hi> and <hi>Labans</hi> parting, <hi>Gen.</hi> 31. 54. and at the <hi>Moabites</hi> friendſhip which they made with <hi>Iſrael, Numb.</hi> 25. 1, 2. And to this the ſtrumpet doth allude, <hi>Prov.</hi> 7. 14. and in <hi>Pſal. 22. v.</hi> 25, 26. the ſame thing is intimated by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of a Spirituall meal whereby the ſoules of believers ſhall be ſatisfied and live for ever. If then to partake of the table of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils, and of Chriſts table, are parallels in oppoſition; and if it is evident not only by the known cuſtome, but by the Apoſtles ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 10. that in partaking of the Idols table, <hi>they did ſit at meat in the Idol-temple;</hi> then it will follow, that thoſe who did partake of the Lords table, did ſit at meat in the Lords temple: For the Apoſtle ſhewing what he means by partaking in reſpect of the one table, doth alſo explain that which is to be underſtood by the ſame word in reſpect of the other.</p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:160191:39"/>
               <p>The third obſervation is, that the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>We all are partakers. We all,</hi> ſheweth that their cuſtome was to be in a Body, and as a Body to partake; and that the whole Body did partake at once, ſo neer as could be. From whence not only the ſeparate partaking, but the ſingle partaking alſo is condemned as a thing unſutable to the Lords ſupper. The practiſe then of the Maſſe-Prieſt to take the bread and wine alone in publike, is hereby condemned; and the private adminiſtration of the Lords ſupper to the ſick (which ſome ignorantly and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly crave, as a <hi>Viaticum itineris ſupremi,</hi> (ſo they call it) the proviſion for their laſt journey) is a corruption of the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: For the words <hi>Many</hi> and <hi>All,</hi> which the Apoſtle doth uſe here, exclude the Adminiſtration unto one alone.</p>
               <p>14. In the eleventh chapter of this ſame Epiſtle, from <hi>v.</hi> 17. till the end, the Apoſtle doth ſpeak of the celebrating of the Lords ſupper; and his ſcope is cleerly, to rectifie the abuſes and diſorders which were crept in amongſt the Corinthians in the uſe of that ordinance: I ſhall open the text, and then make obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, <hi>v.</hi> 17. he reproves them in generall, that they <hi>came together not for the better, but for the worſe;</hi> namely, for the abuſe of this ordinance.</p>
               <p>Then in particular, he tells them what their faults were, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting them for the ſame; and inſtructs them in their duty, ſhewing how the ordinance ſhould be obſerved.</p>
               <p>He diſcovers their faults, from <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. till 22. which are theſe—</p>
               <p>Firſt, that they were divided in ſects, <hi>v. 18, 19. For firſt of all</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when ye come together in the Church, I heare that there be diviſions among you; and I partly believe it; for there must be alſo hereſies</hi> (ſects) <hi>amongſt you, that they which are approved may be made manifeſt among you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, that they did not come together ſo much to eat the Lords ſupper, as their own ſuppers; and that in a divided and exceſſive way, <hi>v. 20, 21. When ye come together therefore into one place, this is not to eat the Lords ſupper; for in eating, every one taketh before other his own ſupper, and one is hungry, and another is drunken.</hi> As if he had ſaid; When ye come together,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:160191:39"/> ye do not ſeem to intend the obſervation of Chriſts ordinance, but the taking of your own meals in ſeverall companies, in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly divided way, and with exceſſe of eating and drinking in ſome, when others are faſting and hungry. Your faults then are, that you come not only divided in opinions and affections, but in your actions and behaviour, you change the Lords ſupper into an ordinary meale; and theſe your meales are taken ſeparately, and in taking of them ſome are exceſſive in drinking, and glut themſelves, while others who partake not with them are hungry. Thus their faults are opened.</p>
               <p>The correction of theſe faults, is in <hi>verſ. 22. What</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>have ye not houſes to eat and to drink? or deſpiſe ye the Church of God, and ſhame them that have not? What ſhall I ſay to you? Shall I praiſe you in this? I praiſe you not.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Do you not know that ye ought not to come together in the Church to eat an ordinary meale? are not private meales to be taken at home in your houſes? By this meanes you make the Church of God contemptible, and the ſociety of Saints a common thing; and you make them aſhamed, that have not made proviſion for entertaining themſelves plentifully as ſome of you do. You diſhonour then the houſe of God, and ſhame your brethren; you deſerve greatly to be blamed for all this, wherein you are extreme faulty.</p>
               <p>Having thus laid their faults open, and corrected them for the ſame; he inſtructs them in their duty, ſhewing them how the Ordinance ſhould be obſerved, in reference to three things. 1. In reſpect of the ordinance in it ſelf, to imitate Chriſts inſtitution. 2. In reſpect of their private preparation, to partake thereof worthily. 3. In reſpect of their publike meeting, to perform the action orderly in the Congregation. The firſt part of the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction concerns the things to be done by Chriſts appointment; the ſecond part, and the third, concerne the perſons doing the ſame, to direct them in the manner of performance, which hath two duties; the one preparatory, wherein every one is apart to fit himſelf for the ordinance; the other executory, wherein all of them are to fit themſelves each towards other in their meeting to that effect.</p>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:160191:40"/>
               <p>The doctrine concerning the Ordinance it ſelf, is <hi>verſ.</hi> 23, 24, 25, 26. where firſt he ſhewes by what authority he doth deliver this doctrine: <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>I have received of the Lord that which I have delivered unto you.</hi> Secondly, he relates unto them what Chriſt did and ſaid in the inſtitution of the Ordinance. Thirdly, he declares unto them what the meaning of their action was, in imitating that which Chriſt did, and remembring what He ſaid.</p>
               <p>Chriſts actions and ſpeeches are diſtinctly related, in reſpect of the time, and in reſpect of the things done and ſaid by him at that time.</p>
               <p>The time was, the night wherein he was betrayed. <hi>That the Lord Jeſus in the ſame night wherein he was betrayed,</hi> v. 23.</p>
               <p>The things done and ſaid by him, relate the two parts of the Ordinance: the firſt, concerning the Bread; the ſecond, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Cup.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Bread, he did three things: He took it, he gave thanks over it, and then brake it. <hi>v. 23, 24. Took bread, and when he had given thanks, he brake it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Concerning the Bread, he ſpake three words: Firſt, a word of command, <hi>Take and eat.</hi> Secondly, a word of inſtitution and conſecration, ſhewing what was meant by the bread, <hi>This (viz.</hi> bread) <hi>is my Body which is broken for you.</hi> And thirdly, a word of direction, inſtructing them what to do, and to what end they ſhould do it; <hi>Do this in remembrance of me.</hi> v. 24.</p>
               <p>Concerning the Cup he relates in like manner that which the Lord did and ſaid.</p>
               <p>That which he did, is expreſſed in theſe words: <hi>After the ſame manner alſo he took the Cup, when he had ſupped,</hi> v. 25.</p>
               <p>That which he ſpake, is in theſe words: <hi>ſaying, this Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood:</hi> Here is the word of inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution and conſecration. And, <hi>This do ye as oft as ye drink it, in remembrance of me:</hi> this is the word of commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and of direction. <hi>v.</hi> 25.</p>
               <p>Hitherto the Apoſtle hath delivered what Chriſt did and ſaid at the appointment of this ordinance: Now, in the verſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:160191:40"/> he delivers unto them doctrinally, what the true meaning and intent of their action is in celebrating the Lords ſupper. <hi>For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as often as ye eat this bread, and drink this cup, ye ſhew the Lords death till he come.</hi> As if he had ſaid, Chriſt having thus appointed his laſt ſupper to be celebrated, by the breaking of bread, and partaking of the cup, for a remembrance of him, and of that which he hath done for us: your imitation of him in this ordinance, in the nature of it, is a ſhewing forth of his death; a teſtimoniall of your faith in his death, till he come again to receive you into life.</p>
               <p>This is the doctrine which is delivered concerning the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance it ſelf, as it is to be celebrated in imitation of Chriſt. Followeth, the doctrine delivered concerning the way to do this worthily, both in reſpect of every Member by himſelfe in particular, and in reſpect of the Body of the Congregation in common.</p>
               <p>The particular Members are taught, 1. What the guilt is of unworthy partaking. 2. How this guilt is to be avoyded. 3. What the puniſhment of unworthy partaking is; with the cauſe deſerving it, and the effect following thereupon. 4. And how both the puniſhment, and the dangerous effect of it is prevented.</p>
               <p>Concerning the guilt of unworthy partaking, the Apoſtle doth inferre it as a conſequence from the foregoing doctrines, thus—<hi>verſ.</hi> 27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wherefore whoſoever ſhall eat this bread, and drink this cup of the Lord unworthily, ſhall be guilty of the body and blood of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That is; Seeing the Lord hath ordained, that the eating of this his bread, and the drinking of his cup, ſhall be the memoriall of his body broken, and of his blood ſhed for us; therefore if any man doth not partake thereof anſwerably to this end, and as it becommeth thoſe that celebrate the memoriall of his death till his comming; he ſhall be guilty before the Lord of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood, as if he were one of thoſe that dealt with him unworthily, and put him to death with wicked &amp; profane hands.</p>
               <p>The way to avoyd this guilt, is to come with a previous exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of ourſelves: this is taught, <hi>v.</hi> 28. in theſe words:</p>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:160191:41"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>But let a man examine himſelf, and ſo let him eat of that bread and drink of that cup.</hi> As if he had ſaid; But if you will free your ſelves from this guilt, you muſt come with due preparation of heart unto the action of the Lords ſupper; and this preparation muſt be a tryall of your ſtate in the preſence of God, ſo as to approve your ſelves in all things to be anſwerable unto his will, in fulfilling the purpoſe of this ordinance.</p>
               <p>Concerning the puniſhment due unto the unworthy partakers, the Apoſtle teacheth them that it is the judgement of dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>v. 29. For</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>he that eateth and drinketh unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily, eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelf.</hi> As if he had ſaid; Be carefull thus to examine and approve your ſelves in the uſe of this ordinance unto God, to anſwer his will; for if you do not ſo, but come unworthily, you ſhall by your eating and drinking procure a judgement of damnation to your ſelves, as a juſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of your ſinne.</p>
               <p>The cauſe deſerving this puniſhment, is their neglect of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and reverence due to God and his ordinance: the Apoſtle calls it, <hi>v.</hi> 29. the <hi>not diſcerning the Lords body;</hi> that is, the want of care and reſpect due to the body of the Lord, not taking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of the dignity and worth of it, nor diſcerning Gods pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in offering it to us, but uſing it as a common thing, doth deſerve this puniſhment.</p>
               <p>The effect following upon this cauſe, in them was, that many of them were weak and ſick, and aſleep. <hi>v. 30. For this cauſe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>many are weak and ſickly among you, and many ſleep.</hi> As if he had ſaid; And becauſe the puniſhment of condemnation is due unto you, therefore God doth afflict you, to ſhew his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure, with outward judgements upon you in the fleſh.</p>
               <p>The means to prevent theſe evils are two: the firſt is our duty, which may prevent the temporall chaſtiſement; the ſecond is Gods dealing with us, to prevent the eternall puniſhment.</p>
               <p>Our duty is to judge our ſelves, whereunto a promiſe is made, that if we perform it, we ſhall not be judged of God. <hi>v. 31. For if we would judge our ſelves, we ſhould not be judged.</hi> As if he had ſaid; Theſe judgements of God befall unto you, becauſe you take not heed to your wayes in his ſervice; for if you did judge and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne your ſelves by repentance for your faults, God would
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:160191:41"/> not thus judge you with ſuch chaſtiſements.</p>
               <p>Gods dealing with us to prevent the eternall evill of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved puniſhment, is, by ſuch chaſtiſements to free us from being condemned with the world. <hi>v. 32. But when</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>we are judged, we are chaſtened of the Lord, that we ſhould not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned with the world.</hi> As if he had ſaid, However theſe cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiſements are juſtly inflicted, and judgements befalling us for want of care to judge our ſelves, and ſhew that we deſerve dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation; yet God doth not inflict them otherwiſe then as a Father doth, to correct us and chaſtiſe us in love, that we may not be condemned finally with the world.</p>
               <p>Thus he hath inſtructed them, how every one ſhould in private behave himſelf in reſpect of this ordinance: Now in the two laſt verſes of the chapter, he doth inſtruct them alſo how they ſhould behave themſelves in publike; and referres them to his comming, for other matters.</p>
               <p>Concerning their publike behaviour in the Church, he ordains two things: Firſt, that they ſhould tarry one for another, and not eat ſeparately; Secondly, that they ſhould not eat to ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their hunger, in the church, but at their houſes.</p>
               <p>Concerning the firſt he ſaith thus, <hi>verſ. 33. Wherefore my brethren, when ye come together to eat, tarry one for another.</hi> Concerning the ſecond he ſaith thus, <hi>verſ. 34. And if any man hunger, let him eat at home, that ye come not together unto con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</hi> As if he had ſaid; Well then, my brethren, let me exhort you to celebrate the Ordinance jointly, and not ſeverally: and to that effect ſtay till you are all met together, to eat bread as one body and company of Saints; and beware, under pain of condemnation, not to uſe this as an ordinary meale to ſatisfie your hunger, but uſe it only for the end to which Chriſt hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed it; and if you be hungry, ſatisfie your appetite at home.</p>
               <p>The reference which he makes of other matters, till his comming, is in theſe words: <hi>The reſt will I ſet in order when I come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>15. Thus I have done with the Analyſis and meaning of the Text; now I ſhall come to ſome brief Obſervations, to fit them to our preſent occaſions.</p>
               <p>Firſt, then, we may take notice of the Corinthians cuſtome;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:160191:42"/> for by the whole context it is apparent that they uſed to come to the Lords ſupper as to a meale; which the Apoſtle doth not at all diſcommend, but only rectifies the abuſe of the meale, by which they were fallen into diſorderly ſeparations, and exceſſes of eating as at a common meal, for hunger. This being avoided, all the reſt of their practiſe is allowed, if they did only come pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paredly, and to the end for which Chriſt did appoint this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, which by the primitive inſtitution was appointed to be a holy meale at his table.</p>
               <p>Secondly, for the outward manner of celebrating this meale by the Congregation, which is the chief thing we now look after, we may obſerve theſe particulars—</p>
               <p n="1">1. That the place where they met to eat, was the Church, and not their houſes; for <hi>v.</hi> 18. he ſaith, <hi>when ye come together in the Church. &amp; v. 20. when ye come together in one place.</hi> Ergo the place was the Church. From whence we may gather, that ſeeing the proper place of this ſacred meale was the Church; the place of their ordinary meales was their private houſes, and it was not lawfull for them to take their ordinary meales in the church, but only at their houſes; therefore it was not lawfull alſo to take the Holy meale at their houſes, but only in the church, that is, at their publike meeting-place: for the Holy meale appointed for a publike meeting, is no leſſe diſproporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate to a private houſe, then an ordinary meale which men take to ſatisfie nature, is diſproportionate to the church of God: <hi>Ergo,</hi> Private communion is not ſutable to Chriſts inſtitution; but the Holy meal is appointed to be in a publike place only, which the Apoſtle calls the Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From this celebrating of a Meale, and in the Church, and ſuch a meale as was to ſatisfie their naturall appetite even as they were wont to do in their private houſes; we may gather cleerly, that the Table-geſture which the <hi>Corinthians</hi> did uſe at their ordinary meales wherein they did eat for hunger, was alſo uſed in the Church at their celebrating of the Lords ſupper. For ſeeing they changed the one into the other, it is not to be queſtioned but that their geſture was the ſame in the one as in the other; and conſequently, that they ſate at the Lords meale, as they did at their own; and if their ſitting at the one had been
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:160191:42"/> more reproveable then at the other, no doubt the Apoſtle would not have left it untouched when he was mentioning their miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>behaviours and abuſes of the ordinance, profeſſedly, to rectifie the ſame. So then, their manner of eating as for the geſture, is allowed, not only becauſe at this time not reproved, but becauſe in the foregoing chap. the Apoſtle doth expreſs himſelf ſo, as doth cleerly import an allowance of the geſture, in making it paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel to the Table-action uſed at the Idol-feaſts, which in <hi>c. 8. v.</hi> 10. he calls <hi>ſitting at meat.</hi> So then to receive the Lords ſupper, as men uſe to do who ſit at their meat, is that which the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> did practiſe with the Apoſtles approbation, and it is that which we ought to imitate in them, and in Chriſt himſelf: and conſequently Kneeling, either at the table or in the pewes, when the Elements are to be received, is altogether unſutable both to the Primitive inſtitution, and to the Apoſtolicall obſervation of this Ordinance.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As we have obſerved here, that the action was a Meale, the place the Church, and the geſture Sitting at meat; ſo we may further take notice from the expreſſion, <hi>v. 18. &amp; 20. When ye come together:</hi> and from the commandement, <hi>v. 33. When ye come together, tarry one for another;</hi> That the whole Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation was to be joyned in this action of eating a meal. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meale was to be at a Table, and the Congregation did come together to eat, and that they are commanded to tarry one for another; it is cleer that their cuſtome was, by the Apoſtles direction, to eat all together of the ſame bread, at the ſame table: which doth again ſhew the unſutableneſſe of eating ſeverally in diſtinct pewes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As for the time, it is cleerly left free to the will of the congregation; for he ſaith no more when he mentions their comming together, but this, <hi>When ye come;</hi> leaving it indefinitely to their will and conveniencie, when they ſhould appoint it: whence we may gather that the Church is not bound to the time wherein Chriſt did celebrate his ſupper; becauſe that circumſtance of time was to the Lord neceſſary to be obſerved, for the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of the law of the Paſſeover to aboliſh it, and to ſubſtitute in the ſtead thereof the memoriall of his death, which now at all times is to be remembred, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 15. we are exhorted to do.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:160191:43"/> And the typicall circumſtance of time which was under the law, being fulfilled, we are now abſolved from that obſervance, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the feaſt which we are to celebrate is a perpetuall feaſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 7, 8. and therefore at all times when the Congregation doth think moſt convenient to meet together to eat, it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable.</p>
               <p>From all which we may gather, that the Apoſtles did herein appoint the Churches to imitate Chriſts practiſe in all things which were proper to the ſolemnity of a Meale, for the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation of the fellowſhip of thoſe that have a right to partake of it, as united together in the Lord. So then, the neerer we come to this practiſe, the more we ſhall be conformable to the will, and anſwer the intention of Chriſt in this his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</p>
               <p>16. Hitherto I have conſidered Chriſt and the Apoſtles pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, and the end and uſe of the Ordinance unto which their practiſe was to be ſubordinate and anſwerable: but becauſe the Apoſtle doth referre us in a ſpeciall manner to take notice of Chriſt himſelf in this matter, let us look a little directly upon Chriſts whole aim and purpoſe in the inſtitution of this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and that we may do this, the things which in his words and actions do inſtitute and diſcover his intentions, are to be reflected upon.</p>
               <p>Firſt then, the words by which he doth conſecrate the bread and wine, are very conſiderable: <hi>This is my Body which is given for you;</hi> and <hi>this Cup is the New Teſtament in my Blood which is ſhed for you,</hi> Luk. 22. 19. 20. by which he ſheweth that his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe was to leave unto his Diſciples, in the uſe of bread and wine, a repreſentation and a pledge of the benefits which by his body and blood were conferred upon their ſoules: therefore he giveth unto the Bread and Cup the names of that whereof they were memorials, repreſentations and pledges; that by a holy uſe thereof in Faith, the things remembred and repreſented thereby might be obtained.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the words of Direction inſtituting the Ordinance for after-times, <hi>Luk. 22. 19. Do this in remembrance of me:</hi> which the Apoſtle doth explain, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 6. to be a <hi>ſhewing of the Lords death till he come;</hi> do manifeſt that his intention was,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:160191:43"/> that they ſhould imitate his practiſe in his laſt Supper, to keep the memory of his death in their mind, till his comming.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, there is a word of promiſe relating to his comming again, and to the conjunction of his Diſciples with him in his kingdom. <hi>Mat. 26. 29. I ſay unto you, I will not drink henceforth of this fruit of the Vine, untill that day when I drink it new with you in my Fathers kingdome.</hi> This promiſe is mentioned alſo, <hi>Mar.</hi> 14. 25. and more generally, in <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 16, 19. and more diſtinct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in <hi>verſ.</hi> 29, 30. where he promiſeth his diſciples <hi>a Kingdome,</hi> and a priviledge <hi>to eat and drink at his table in his kingdome.</hi> All which doth cleerly intimate, that his intention was by this Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance not only to aſſure them of his comming again, but of their ſociety and fellowſhip with him, whereof this Meale was to be an earneſt and demonſtration. So then he did intend that this Feaſt upon the ſacrifice of his Body and Blood, ſhould be unto them not only a means to confirm their Faith in his death, and in the effects thereof in the New Teſtament, as a thing paſt, but alſo of their hope of the ſtate of life to come. So that this Feaſt was appointed to demonſtrate alſo our expectation of the Feaſt which is prepared for thoſe that are to be with the Lambe at his wedding, <hi>Revel.</hi> 19. 9.</p>
               <p>Fourthly and laſtly, Chriſts action of <hi>ſerving his Diſciples</hi> at his laſt meale with them, doth ſpeak much of his intention to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them: for he thereby doth not only intend to give them an example of humility, that they ſhould ſerve one another, as he expreſly doth mention (<hi>Joh.</hi> 13. 12. till 17. &amp; <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 27.) that he did ſerve them; but this ſervice at his laſt meals, doth ſpeak them to be his loving friends and familiars, as <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 15. he calls them: It doth ſpeak them his gueſts who did ſit at meat at his table, as he declares it <hi>Luk.</hi> 22. 27. and conſequently it doth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt unto them and us, that his intention was to ſhew forth unto them, and in their perſons ſo entertained by him, to give to all his faithfull ſervants by this Ordinance an aſſurance of the eſteem which he hath of them now, and will have of them for ever in his Kingdome, For elſewhere, viz. <hi>Luk.</hi> 12. 37. there is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe promiſe made unto all his Faithfull ſervants, aſſuring them of the like entertainment; the words are theſe: <hi>Bleſſed are the ſervants whom the Lord when he commeth ſhall find watching,</hi> (and conſequently faithfull to him in their charges) <hi>Verily I
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:160191:44"/> ſay unto you, that He ſhall gird himſelf, and make them ſit down to meat, and will come forth and ſerve them.</hi> This then being pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed unto all, and performed by the Lord unto his diſciples at the laſt Meale, whereof the remembrance is to be kept by all; is a cleer demonſtration, that Chriſts intention was towards them, and is to all his faithfull diſciples, by the ſolemnity of the action to give us an aſſurance of his love &amp; eſteem of us, that he accounts us as his friends &amp; familiar gueſts whom he doth honor.</p>
               <p>17. From all which, this Concluſion as a generall rule is to be gathered in this matter; Namely,</p>
               <p>That manner of Adminiſtration of the Lords ſupper is moſt warrantable, which doth beſt expreſſe and imitate Chriſt and his Apoſtles practiſe in the uſe of this Ordinance; which doth repreſent and hold forth moſt effectually all Chriſts intentions in it; and which is moſt fit to accompliſh moſt fully the commandement of celebrating the Memoriall both of his death, and of our conjunction with him at his comming again.</p>
               <p>And on the other ſide, that manner of Adminiſtration is leaſt warrantable, which doth not anſwer and imitate Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles practiſe in the uſe of this ordinance; which doth not repreſent and hold forth any of Chriſts in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions in it; and which is not at all fitted to accompliſh in any competent meaſure, the commandement of celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the memoriall both of his Death, and of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with him at his comming again.</p>
               <p>But it is now made apparent by that which hath been hitherto ſaid, that a Table-geſture in ſitting at meat, doth beſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and imitate Chriſt and his Apoſtles practiſe in the uſe of this ordinance; That it doth repreſent and hold forth moſt effectually all Chriſts intentions in it; and that it is moſt fit to accompliſh his commandement of celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the memorial of his death, and of our conjunction with him at his coming again. And on the other ſide it hath alſo been made apparent, that the geſture of Kneeling, or any other behaviour inconſiſtent with a Table-action, at a meal, is leaſt anſwerable and proper to all this.</p>
               <p>Therefore it followeth, that the Table-geſture of fitting at meat is that manner of Adminiſtration of the Lords ſupper which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:160191:44"/> is moſt warrantable; and that the geſture of Kneeling is leaſt warrantable in this Adminiſtration.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The practiſe of the beſt Reformed Churches, in the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the LORD'S Supper.</head>
               <p>HAving hitherto taken from the Word of GOD, the grounds which make good this Concluſion; I ſhall adde for a cloſe of this Diſcourſe, a brief Relation of the Practiſe of the beſt Reformed Churches; to ſhew how in their Publike meetings this Ordinance is obſerved by them, in imitation &amp; remembrance of the Lord.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They appoint commonly the Lords day, in the morning, for the time of partaking of the Lords table; and in moſt places this is done every two moneths once.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Miniſter, after morning-Sermon, when he hath pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and cauſed the Pſalm to be ſung, and diſmiſſed thoſe that are not to partake; doth ſpeak by way of Exhortation to thoſe that are to come to the Ordinance; declaring the inſtitution thereof, the benefits to be received by the worthy partakers in it, and the danger of unworthy partaking: whereupon the impenitent and ſcandalous are warned not to preſume to approch unto the table.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This Exhortation is by ſome delivered in the Pulpit, by ſome at the Table it ſelf; by ſome it is read out of a Book where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Conceived form by the Church is contained, by others it it not read, but delivered in a free diſcourſe: for although they have Forms, yet they do not ſtrictly bind their Miniſters to them.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There is a Table, before the beginning of the Sermon, covered with a clean cloth upon it; and at the end where the Miniſter is to ſit, the bread and wine is ſet prepared, to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated by him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. When the Miniſter hath ended the Exhortation prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory to the action, before the conſecration of the Elements he giveth thanks, and prayeth unto God for a bleſſing upon the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and upon thoſe that do partake of it. This prayer is made at the Table, whiles the Miniſter is there alone; the prayer being ended, he invites the Communicants to approach orderly without noiſe and confuſion,</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:160191:45"/>6. The Elders and Deacons, in moſt places, partake firſt with the Miniſter; and when theſe have received, they riſe and ſerve the tables, which afterward are filled.</p>
               <p n="7">7. According to the bigneſſe of the Congregation, and the conveniencie of the place, the Table is made longer or ſhorter, and-Forms are ſet on each ſide thereof at a convenient diſtance, for people to ſit, and to go in and out, and they are ordered by the Elders to go in at the one end of the Table on each ſide, and out at the other, every one following his neighbour; and as every one doth approach, he giveth unto the Elder ſtanding at the ſide of the Table whereat he enters, his Token.</p>
               <p n="8">8. At every time the Table is filled, the Miniſter doth repeat the words of Conſecration uſed by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> or to that effect; and diſtributeth firſt the Bread, on both hands, to thoſe that ſit next unto him; and then doth ſhove the Veſſell which containeth the conſecrated bread, unto the reſt along the Table as they ſit in order, every one taking of it as it comes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him a morſell; and the Elders of each ſide ſtand behind the Communicants to ſhove the Veſſell along the Table, for the quicker diſpatch of the action, and to bring up the Veſſell from the lower to the upper end where the Miniſter doth ſit, when all have eaten of the bread that is in it.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The Bread being diſtributed, the Cup in like manner is conſecrated, and given by the Miniſter on each hand one cup, to go all along from one to another; every one when he hath taſted of the wine, ſetting it down upon the table before his neighbour, and he taking it up, drinking of it, and ſetting it down again; and when all have drunk, the Elders carry up the Cups to the end where the Miniſter ſits, and ſet them filled before him; and a Bleſſing being pronounced upon each Table-full, the Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants riſe in order, and go to their ſeats, and another Table-full doth come in their room, till all have received.</p>
               <p n="10">10. The men come firſt in order, &amp; then the women to partake.</p>
               <p n="11">11. There is a Baſon held or ſet in ſome place, at the end of the table, where the people come in or goe out, to receive a collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the poor. 12. When all have received, the laſt Table-full doth ſit ſtil at the table until the Miniſter be gone up again to the Pulpit, to give thanks to God for all, and to diſmiſſe the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation with a bleſſing.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
